<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England's great interest, by encouraging the setting up the royal fishery within the British seas With some political observations out of divers authors; treating of the manifold advantages by sea and land, from the fishing trade. As also, an impartial account of the proceedings of the corporation to this time. Published by approbation and allowance of the Company of the Royal Fishery of England. For encouraging the people of these nations, &amp;c. to improve the advantages therof, under the countenance and privilege granted to the Company and their successors, by his late Majesty King Charles II. in letters patents under the Great Seal of England; bearing date 25th day of September, in the 29th year of his said Majesty's reign.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B22505</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827874</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207630</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240885702</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2973</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827874</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99827874e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B22505)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207630)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1924:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England's great interest, by encouraging the setting up the royal fishery within the British seas With some political observations out of divers authors; treating of the manifold advantages by sea and land, from the fishing trade. As also, an impartial account of the proceedings of the corporation to this time. Published by approbation and allowance of the Company of the Royal Fishery of England. For encouraging the people of these nations, &amp;c. to improve the advantages therof, under the countenance and privilege granted to the Company and their successors, by his late Majesty King Charles II. in letters patents under the Great Seal of England; bearing date 25th day of September, in the 29th year of his said Majesty's reign.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for H.M. and are to be sold by J. Whitlock near Stationers-Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Fisheries --  History --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Fishery law and legislation --  History --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Fishery management --  History --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207630:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207630:1"/>
            <p>ENGLAND's Great Interest, By Encouraging the Setting up the ROYAL FISHERY Within the BRITISH SEAS.</p>
            <p>With some Political Observations out of divers Authors; Treating of the manifold Advantages by Sea and Land, from the Fishing Trade.</p>
            <p>As also, An Impartial Account of the Proceedings of the Corporation to this time.</p>
            <p>Published by Approbation and Allowance of the Company of the <hi>Royal Fishery</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Encouraging the People of these Nations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to improve the Advantages thereof, under the Countenance and Privilege granted to the Company and their Successors, by his late Majesty King <hi>Charles</hi> II. in Letters Patents under the Great Seal of <hi>England;</hi> bearing Date 25th day of <hi>September,</hi> in the 29th year of his said Majesty's Reign.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>H. M.</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>J. Whitlock</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1695.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:207630:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207630:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:207630:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:207630:3"/>
            <head>A COLLECTION, With some Observations, touching the Royal Fishery OF Great BRITAIN and IRELAND.</head>
            <p>THE Fishery Trade has been the Subject of many Discourses. Some have attempted the thing amongst us, but so, as if they had, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not duly reckon'd up the Cost, Charge, and Hazard of it, or thought they might make it their Recreation, or a meer matter of Notion and Contemplation, yea Admiration, (as indeed it is) rather than their Serious and Diligent employ: And so applying to it, it has thriven with them accordingly.</p>
            <p>The Wisdom of this Nation in Parliament has provided for it, by many good Laws, for incouraging and regulating Undertakers therein; that it might be to the Nations advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and have continuance. Our Statute-books are full of them, in the Reigns of several of our Princes, Kings and Queens: And many Proclamations have been issued, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the same.</p>
            <p>It has also been the care of some of our Princes, to As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert and Challenge their singular Interest in, and sole Right and Title to the Fishery of the British and Irish Seas; which our Neighbours have some time allowed, and paid, and do still pay our Royal Navy the respect of their Flag for; and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:207630:4"/> till of late, accepted yearly Licenses for their partaking with us in.</p>
            <p>There are Presidents enough, and some of no mean Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Esteem for Learning and Experience, who have high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provoked the Ingenuity of such an Undertaking. Some of our own Countrey-men, who have met with it in their Travels, and reported the fame of it. Others of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, who have practicably and profitably applyed themselves, and stirr'd up their Brethren to all diligence and heed therein, that it might be retained as a rich Golden Mine, amongst themselves; and their Gains convince all Gain-sayers, that it has been so to them.</p>
            <p>But these things may be Waved; There's Fish enough for us all: And it may not be convenient in this Publication, to meddle with the politique part of this Affair, farther than by glancing upon such particulars as lye in common to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and Private Advantages thereof.</p>
            <p>This Collection, therefore, is intended principally to be confined to such Considerations, as may incite the People of these Kingdoms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to improve a share thereof to their own Advantage, by ingaging in a Joint Stock for carrying on the same; to be raised in way and manner as is Proposed, by the Company of the Royal Fishery of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In order whereunto, Two things are offered to Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, by these Collections.</p>
            <p>The First is, A Narrative of what Attempts have been made, under what Incouragements, with what Stocks, and how the Undertakers have Succeeded, to the intent that all may be truly Informed and Cautioned. The Next is, How all miscarriages therein may be Remedied and Amended, and whence we may ground our Confidence, That in a due Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement thereof, as is Proposed, we cannot miss a desired Effect, <hi>Favente Deo▪</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>For the First, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The late Right Honourable <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> Sir <hi>William Courteen,</hi> Sir <hi>John Harrison,</hi> and Sir <hi>Paul Pindar,</hi> in or about the year 1633, became an Association, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and for their incouragement therein, His then Majesty King <hi>Charles</hi> the First,</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1. Caused Lent to be Observed.</item>
                  <item n="2">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:207630:4"/> 2. Prohibited Foreign Fish to be Imported.</item>
                  <item n="3">3. Took his Naval Supplies from the then Adventurers in that Fishing Trade.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Afterwards, <hi>viz.</hi> In or about the year 1654. Sir <hi>Phineas An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews, &amp;c.</hi> proceeding on the Fishery Trade, for his Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it was provided.</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1. That Salt spent in the Fishery Trade, was exempted from Customs and Excise.</item>
                  <item n="2">2. Collections were Granted and made in <hi>London</hi> and other Places, for Building of Docks, Wharfs, Store-houses, and Renting of Ground, for the Making, Tanning, Dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Mending Nets.</item>
                  <item n="3">3. Also Exemption from Custom and Excise, of all Naval Necessaries, as Timber, Cordage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> used on such oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions.</item>
               </list>
               <p>After him, <hi>viz.</hi> In or about the year 1660. the said Fishery was undertaken by <hi>Simon Smith,</hi> Esq; for whose Incouragement was Granted.</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1. All the forementioned Advantages. And</item>
                  <item n="2">2. That all Commodities returned for the Produce of Fish, were allowed to be Imported Custom free.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Upon the Restauration of his late Majesty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, by Commission under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> bearing date the 22d day of <hi>August,</hi> in the 13th year of his Reign, his said Majesty was pleased to Constitute his Royal Highness, <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York, Edward</hi> Earl of <hi>Clarenden,</hi> and other Persons of Honour and Wisdom, to be a Council of the Royal Fishery of Great <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> of which his said Majesty was pleased to Declare,</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1. That Himself and his Successors would vouchsafe ever to be, and to be called Protectors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="2">2. The said Council were Authorized thereby to make Laws and Statutes, relating to the management of the said Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, and Government of all their Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="3">3. To Constitute and Depute Officers necessary for their Service.</item>
                  <item n="4">4. To enjoyn pecuniary Mulcts or Pains of Imprisonment, on Contemners and Violaters of the said Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being not derogatory to the Statutes, Laws, Liberties, or Acts of Parliament.</item>
                  <item n="5">5. Their Fishermen, Mariners, Masters and Servants were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:207630:5"/> to be Free from all Pleas or Plaints in any Courts of Justice, for any thing concerning the Fishery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> except before the said Council or Judges, to be by them Deligated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="6">6. Their Fishermen nor Boats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (whether at Sea or in Port) were to be Arrested or Impressed for his Majesties Service or Affairs, without the Consent of their Owners.</item>
                  <item n="7">7. Nor put in Assizes, Juries, Inquisitions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor made Collectors, nor compelled to be Constables or Tithing-men, against their Wills.</item>
                  <item n="8">8. The said Council were Authorized to set up a Lottery for Three Years, and to appoint a free Collection in Churches, for raising of Monies to be imployed for erecting Wharfs, Docks, Store-houses, and Granaries about the River of <hi>Thames,</hi> and all Ports convenient for that purpose.</item>
                  <item n="9">9. That, for the space of Seven Years, from their first en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance upon the Fishing Trade, no Customs, Inward or Outward were to be paid for the Sale of Fish, either in the Baltick Seas, <hi>Denmark, Norway,</hi> or <hi>France.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="10">10. That they might freely vend their Fish in Foreign Parts, and make Returns thereof in the Commodities of the Place, without Interruption, by vertue of any Power or Charter whatsoever to the contrary.</item>
                  <item n="11">11. That all Victuallers, Inns, Ale-houses, Taverns, Coffee-houses, and the like, should take One, Two, Three, Four, or more Barrels of Herrings yearly, at the price of Thirty Shillings <hi>per</hi> Barrel, until Foreign vent should be attained to Perfection, according as the said Council should order the same.</item>
                  <item n="12">12. That all Barrels of Pickled Herrings and Cod-fish that should be brought into <hi>England,</hi> by the <hi>Flemmings</hi> or others, should pay Two Shillings Six Pence <hi>per</hi> Barrel to the Stock of that Place or Port, where they shall vend the same.</item>
                  <item n="13">13. That in case of breach of Peace with any Foreign Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his Majesty did Promise and Grant, the said Fishery should be protected in their Fishing grounds; and should have Convoies for their Exportation of Fish.</item>
                  <item n="14">14. That all other Privileges and Immunities should be Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them, in future, as Experience should discover, for the better carrying on of this business of the Royal Fishing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But, according to the Proverb, <hi>They had other Fish to Fry.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:207630:5"/>
               <p> All which notwithstanding, and that an Affair of such a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional concern might be the better promoted; and at, and upon the Advice and Request of the said Council, for Incorporating a Company; in order thereunto his said late Majesty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, was pleased, by his Letters Patents under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> bearing date the 25th day of <hi>September,</hi> in the 29th year of his Reign, <hi>(viz</hi> about Sixteen Years after, during which time little or nothing had been done) to Constitute his said Royal Highness <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York, Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> (now Duke of <hi>Leeds)</hi> and several other Persons of Honour, and others therein named: And such others as therein after from time to time should be admitted into their Company and Society, to be Traders and Adventurers with them; to be one Body Politick and Corporate, in Deed and in Name, by the Name of <hi>The Company of the Royal Fishery of</hi> England, to have perpetual Succession, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thereby also giving and granting unto the said Company and their Successors, divers beneficial Clauses, Grants, Powers, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges and Immunities, in order to the better Government of the said Company, and Management of their Affairs; an Abstract whereof here followeth: <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1. To purchase Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments; and to dispose thereof, to the value of One thousand Pounds <hi>per Annum.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="2">2. To have and use a Common Seal, in and for all Causes and Businesses of the said Company.</item>
                  <item n="3">3. To assemble and meet together, for carrying on their Affairs. And particularly,</item>
                  <item n="4">4. To Elect and Appoint a Governour, Sub-Governour, Deputy-Governour, and Twelve Committees yearly, for a Court of Assistants; who, (or any Three or more of them, whereof the Governour, Sub-Governour, or Deputy-Governour, to be always One) are thereby au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized to act in all things according to such Rules, Orders, and Directions, as should from time to time be made and given unto them, by the General Court: And for want of such Orders, Rules and Directions, to Manage, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, Direct, and Do, what they should judge necessary and expedient, to the well Ordering and Government of the said Company, and the improvement of their Joint Stock and Trade, to all intents and purposes, as if the same were done at, and by a General Court of the said Company.</item>
                  <item n="5">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:207630:6"/> 5. That the said Court of Assistants, or any seven or more of them, as aforesaid, as often as they shall find occasion, may Summon a General Court.</item>
                  <item n="6">6. That no Assembly or Meeting of the said Company shall be deemed a General Court, unless the Governour, Sub-Governour, or Deputy-Governour, six of the said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees, and five other Members of the Company, at least, be present.</item>
                  <item n="7">7. That such General Court may admit other Persons to be Members, and may Increase, Contract, or Divide their Joynt-Stock, as they shall think fit: And the Members thereof may Grant, Transfer, and Assign their respective Stocks, as is therein mentioned.</item>
                  <item n="8">8. That such General Court may Ordain and Establish such Laws, Ordinances, Orders, and Constitutions, as to them shall seem convenient, for the Government of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and their Affairs: And may Impose and set Mulcts and Amerciaments upon the Breakers of such Laws: Or may Remit, Pardon, or Release the same, upon the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Submission. And, upon Conviction of any Misde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor, may remove Offenders, and choose others.</item>
                  <item n="9">9. That they may Fish in and upon all the Coasts, Creeks, In-lets, Estuaries, Rivers, Lakes, and Arms of the Sea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to His Majesty's Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> or any of them; or any other His Majesty's Dominions, whereof the Fishings are not already Granted, Appropriated, or Belonging to some particular or private Person or Persons, Bodies Politique or Corporate. And likewise, in and upon the Main Sea, or any part thereof. And have free and full Liberty to carry and Transport their Fish, and Oyl made of Fish, to all Ports, Places, and Markets, both in <hi>England</hi> and beyond the Seas; and to Sell the same for ready Moneys, or Commodities.</item>
                  <item n="10">10. That they may erect Store-houses, Granaries, Ware-houses, Work-houses: And may Build and make Wharffs and Docks in and upon any of His Majesty's Wastes, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, or Wast-grounds adjoyning unto, or upon any Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Rivers or Seas, within any His Majesty's Dominions, without paying or rendring any Rent or Duty to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty for the same.</item>
                  <item n="11">
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:207630:6"/> 11. That neither their Masters, Skippers, Steers-men, Ship's-Crews, Mariners, Fishermen, nor others employed by the Company in their Fishings, whether Foreigners or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, shall be Impannel'd, Sworn, or compelled to Serve on any Juries or Inquests at <hi>Westminster,</hi> the Assizes, Ses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, or elsewhere.</item>
                  <item n="12">12. They have also granted unto them the Yearly Sum of Twenty Pounds for each and every Dogger which they had, and which within seven years they should Build in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or any other His Majesty's Dominions; the same to be paid Quarterly out of the Customs within the Port of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> without further Warrant or Directions from His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty. Also, all and singular Priviledges in the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> as fully and freely as any Company of Merchants, established by Letters Pattents or Charters, do or may have, use, or enjoy.</item>
                  <item n="13">13. That all and singular Admiral, Vice-Admirals, General, Commanders, Captains, Mayors, Sheriffs, Justices of the Peace, Custom-house Officers, and all other Officers, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, Liege People and Subjects of His Majesty's what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, shall be, in and by all things Aiding and Assisting to the said Company and their Successors, their Factors, Agents, and Servants, in the Execution and Enjoyment of the Premisses, as well on Land as by Sea, whensoever they shall be thereunto desired: As they tender His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty's Good-Will and Pleasure, and will answer the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary at their Peril, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As in and by the said Letters Patents, Relation being thereunto had for the better cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty thereof, may more fully and at large appear.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Company being thus Established, divers particular Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof advanced and paid in, as a Stock, at first, Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand, Nine Hundred and Eighty Pounds: And, after that, about Sixteen Hundred Pounds more. Which was laid out in Buying, Equipping, and Setting forth several Fishing Vessels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying of them in prosecuting the said Fishery Affairs. But that Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking was rendred ineffectual, and their said small Stock soon exhausted and consumed, [Not by any thing arising from the Nature of the thing it self (as was apparent by the Experience the said Company had, in having taken and Imported in one of their Doggers, (in a Voyage of but three Weeks) Thirty two
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:207630:7"/> Thousand Cods, and proportionably thereunto in several other of their Vessels; and by the Advantage ordinarily made of the like Undertaking by our Neighbours, (which shall be demonstrated by some Narrative thereof, with particular Enumeration of their ordinary Successes in what follows) But] by that ill Juncture of Affairs, wherein the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> were engaged in War with the <hi>French,</hi> who seized the Vessels and Goods of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, as <hi>Dutch,</hi> being some, or most of them <hi>Dutch-</hi>built, and Mann'd: And principally because the Stock was not sufficient to support so great an Undertaking, in case of any Misadventure.</p>
               <p>And the Company consisting then principally of the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Persons Nominated and Incorporated by the Letters Patents before recited, and they having also received in, admitted, and sworn several other Persons as Members thereof; they, looking into the Affairs of the Company, and finding them to be in Debt, upon the Accounts aforesaid, and not likely to get out, but by a further Subscription and Advance of Moneys, as well for clearing off the said Debts, as for promoting and carrying on the said Trade in future, Proposed the same might be done by a New Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of the then Members of the Company, to the Value of Thirty Thousand Pounds, or Twenty Thousand Pounds at least. Which was accordingly agreed unto by the General Court, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Towards which, Eleven of the Members of the said Company only, <hi>(viz.</hi> of such of them as had been added to the Company as aforesaid) began the Advance for Paying off the Debts, and also gave Bonds of 1000 <hi>l.</hi> each, as was agreed on, for paying 500 <hi>l.</hi> apiece to the Treasurer of the Company, towards a Stock for Entering thereupon, <hi>de Novo,</hi> Expecting the Patentees would have done the like, which was declined. Nevertheless, several Meetings both of the Company in general, and of the Court of Assistants of the said Company, were appointed to consider how it might be done by other Persons; and to receive Proposals from any Persons for that purpose, and to Report the same with their Opinions, and such Articles of Agreement touching the same, as they should judge might be most for the Advantage of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and Promoting the said Trade: Which, after several Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Reports made of their Proceedings to the said Company at their General Court, produced a Draught of a certain Deed, Entituled, <hi>Articles of Agreement between the Company of the Royal Fishery of</hi> England <hi>of the one Part, and Sir</hi> Edward Abney, <hi>Knight, &amp;c. of the other Part;</hi> which were agreed unto, and ordered to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:207630:7"/> be Ingrossed, in order to the perfecting and confirming the same, under the Seal of the said Company, which was accordingly done on the Second day of <hi>April,</hi> 1683. Which, for as much as the clearing the Right and Title of the present Members of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, (exclusive of the said Patentees) may be of use for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viating of any pretence of Objection, against the same: The Collector hath thought it convenient to insert the Abstract there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, under the Heads or several Sections following: <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. There is express mention and recital of the Names of all the original Patentees, and of their being Incorporated by the said Letters Patents, for the carrying on the said Affairs, by them and their Successors for ever, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. There is, in like manner, a Recital of the Names of such of the said Patentees as were then Deceased; and as had assigned and transferred their Interests to any others, and particularly to whom.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That upon consideration of the ill state of their Affairs, and the Debts they had Contracted in the Management thereof, they did order their whole remaining Stock should be Sold, for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Debts, which was accordingly done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Notice is taken, [and mention made thereof, <hi>viz.]</hi> That the Trade and Being of the said Company might have then deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined with their Stock, if some Persons therein named, upon Proposals made for entering upon a new Undertaking and Stock, for reviving and carrying on thereof, had not assisted, by raising a New Stock of 2600 <hi>l.</hi> which was also consumed and spent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. That the said Company, at a General Court held the 8th of <hi>March,</hi> 1682. Declared it was necessary for carrying on the said Trade; that a Stock of 30000 <hi>l.</hi> or at least of 20000 <hi>l.</hi> should be raised with all convenient speed: And that all and every of the then living Members of the said Company, should at or before the 26th day of the said Month of <hi>March,</hi> Subscribe, and firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oblige himself in a Bond of 1000 <hi>l.</hi> to <hi>John Collins,</hi> Secretary to the said Company, to advance and pay 500 <hi>l.</hi> to <hi>Richard Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> Esq; their then Treasurer, for their Adventures in the Stock of the said Company, in time and manner therein set forth. And that every Person failing to make such Subscription, Bond and Payment, should forfeit 3 <hi>l. per Cent. per mensem,</hi> until he should comply there with.</p>
               <p n="6">6. For the Incouragement of Persons to become Adventurers in the Stock, and promote the Concern, in the room of such as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207630:8"/> should not Subscribe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It was ordered, That any Five of the Court of Assistants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> should receive any Proposals that might be advantageous to the Company: As also, to Treat, Contract, and Agree with the Proposers thereof, for their being Admitted into, and Incorporated with the said Company: And to prepare and perfect Articles of Agreement, touching such Proposals as they should judge might be Advantageous to the Company; to be confirmed by some legal Instrument in writing, under the Seal of the Company.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Notice is taken, That Eleven Persons and no more of the then Members of said said Company had, in pursuance of the Order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned, Subscribed to advance their said respective Shares, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that the same, if brought in, would not be sufficient for carrying on the said Trade, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. It Recites also, That Sir <hi>Edward Abney,</hi> Knight, and others joined with him, being willing, as Members, to advance and bring in a farther Stock, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had made certain Proposals in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suance of the forementioned Order, of the 12th of <hi>March,</hi> for the Erecting and Establishing a Bank of Credit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which might have been useful to their Affair.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Also that the Committees appointed by the Company on the 28th of <hi>March,</hi> 1683. after several Debates and Alterations made of the Proposals, had come to an Agreement with the said Sir <hi>Edward Abney, &amp;c.</hi> And that they Proposed, Reported, and offered it as their Opinion, That the said Articles of Agreement, so altered and amended, should be Ratified and Confirmed at a General Court of the said Company, under the Seal of the said Company; which was accordingly done the 2d of <hi>April,</hi> 1683. in the Particulars following, (among others) <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Persons whose names are therein Recited, and such others as they should nominate (not exceeding (together with themselves) in the whole, the Number of 22 Persons. And also, That the said Sir <hi>Edward Abney, &amp;c.</hi> (therein also particularly recited) and such others as shall be joined as Governours or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the Bank, not exceeding (together with themselves) the Number of 23 Persons more; and no other, or greater Number than 45 Persons in the whole, shall be by the said Persons respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively so Named, Chosen, Admitted or Allowed to be of the Company of the Royal Fishery of <hi>England.</hi> But, in case one or more of the late Members of the Company, who have not Subscribed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or shall not pay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as aforesaid, shall at any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:207630:8"/> time or times hereafter, be Admitted or allowed to Be or to Act, or shall Act as a Member or Members of the said Company, whereby the Number of the said Company shall exceed Forty Five Persons in the whole, that then the said Sir <hi>Edward Abney, &amp;c.</hi> and such others as shall be joyned unto them, as the Governours or Masters of the said Bank, or the major part of them, shall have liberty to nominate the like number of Persons, in Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of such additional number; and that they shall be admitted into the Company to such further number.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the said whole Company shall be reduced, as soon as may be, to the said Number of Forty Five Persons, or fewer; but not under 28 Persons: And that in Order thereunto, no Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or Persons, former Members of the said Company, who have failed to Subscribe and secure his Proportion, shall for the future Act or Vote in any of the Affairs of the said Company, without the Consent of at least two Third Parts of the said Company.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the said Company, or such Number or Committees of them, as, according to the said Letters Patents, and these Articles of Agreement, shall be from time to time chosen in, may, to all intents and purposes, Act, in all matters and things whatsoever, relating to the Fishery Trade, as if they and every of them had been by Name exprest in and by the said Letters Patents: And that no other or further Number of Persons shall be at any time admitted to Act or Vote as Members of the said Company, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the consent of at least three fourth Parts of the said whole Number of the said Company and their Successors, in a General Court of the said Company, Summon'd for that purpose; and Meeting in such manner and place as is therein after agreed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That the Bank of Credit and Governours or Masters thereof shall receive and be capable of all Powers, Priviledges, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities whatsoever, which the same is or can, by Counsel learned in the Law, be made capable of Receiving and taking of in or by reason of the said Corporation or Company of the Royal Fishery of <hi>England,</hi> and their Charter of Incorporation, without Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to the Royal Fishery Trade.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That whatsoever shall be concluded and agreed upon by the Committees of the Company of the Royal Fishery of <hi>England,</hi> agreeable to the Orders and Directions of a General Court, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> shall be binding in what concerns the Royal Fishery Trade only: And that whatsoever shall be concluded, agreed, and acted by the Governours, Masters, and Chief Managers of the Bank, or any three or more of them, only shall be binding in what concerns
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:207630:9"/> the Affairs of the Bank. And that all shall be deemed the Acts of the Company of the Royal Fishery of <hi>England,</hi> and have Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, Grants, and Confirmations under the Seal thereof, where they shall respectively propose and desire or order the same.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That before any Person be admitted to be a Member of the said Company, he shall oblige himself to Observe, Abide by, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, and Confirm these present Articles of Agreement, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever shall be done in pursuance thereof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As by the said Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Agreement, Relation being thereunto had for the better certainty thereof, may more fully and at large appear.</p>
               <p>So then, 'tis evident that the present Members of the Company, consisting of the Persons particularly named and exprest in the said Articles, for carrying on and management of the Trade and Affairs of the said Royal Fishery, and such others as by them have been since taken in, and added, as Members, Traders, or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers with them, are the Legal and Rightful Company of the Royal Fishery of <hi>England,</hi> exclusive of the said Patentees. And that their Proceedings thereupon, and all Acts, Orders, Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Laws, and Rules by them made, for the Government and Management of their Affairs; and in Order to the Raising a New Stock for that purpose, are unquestionable, and without the least pretence of Irregularity or Prejudice to any Persons formerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned therein.</p>
               <p>Since when, the Prosecution of the Affairs and Trade of the said Company hath been under the Care and Management of the said Persons: Who have been endeavouring the Setting up the same by New Subscriptions, designed and agreed by them to the value of Sixty Thousand Pounds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But by reason of the Death of his said late Majesty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and the Troubles ensuing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The same was thought fit to be suspended for some further time.</p>
               <p>And the Company, about three Years since, (conceiving it might be seasonably undertaken) Assembled for putting their said former Design in Execution: And finding Encouragement, from the readiness of divers Persons to joyn therein, upon several Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posals for a Subscription, such as, in case of like Losses of some few Vessels, the said Affair might, notwithstanding, be carried on, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Discouragement of being to seek of a Stock ready; They have been ever since waiting for a fitting Season, wherein they might Humbly Address themselves to His Majesty, and both the Honourable Houses of Parliament (without Interruption of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:207630:9"/> great Affair of providing for, and carrying on the War) for their encouraging this Undertaking. And,</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Interim,</hi> that no further time may be lost in Preparations for this Undertaking (which the Parliament, by their Act past in <hi>Anno</hi> 13 <hi>&amp;</hi> 14 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 28. have declared, The Publick Honour, Wealth, and Safety of this Realm, as well in the Maintenance of Trade and Support of Navigation, as in many other Respects, doth in an High Degree depend upon the Improvement of the Fishery,) The Company have spent their time, and taken much pains, and been at considerable Costs and Charges, in and about the Consul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Consideration, and Preparation of such a Constitution, Laws, and Rules, for Management and Governing of their said Affairs; and framing such Articles, Terms, or Conditions for Admitting Persons into the said Company, to be Members, Traders, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers with them therein, as, by Discoursing others, they hope will be sufficiently Encouraging to Subscriptions, for the raising such Stock for that purpose. And, whereby His Majesty and the Parliament may be the better satisfied, That Persons of Honour, Interest, Estates, and Publick Spirits, yea, the whole Nation are, and may reasonably be imagined, will think themselves concerned, joyntly to become engaged to carry on and stand by the same, as far as the Nature of such an Affair will admit. And,</p>
               <p>In order thereunto, the Company have thought fit, to cause, as well the said Letters Patents, as the said Constitution and terms of Subscription, to be fairly Engross'd at large, in Books to be expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed for Subscriptions of a Present Stock of Three Hundred Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Pounds, or of One Hundred and Fifty Thousand Pounds (at least) to begin withal, Payable at Ten Quarterly Payments, in Equal Proportions, (which makes the Raising of it very easie) the Time and Place of which Subscriptions will be seasonably Advertised, in order to these Books being perused and considered by such as shall think fit to Resort thereto for their Information. And,</p>
               <p>For as much as all Persons (especially such as live remote) may not have the Conveniency of their perusal; and that the Affair may become as National and Comprehensive of all, as may be (which is the Design and Desire of the Company,) and none have cause to think themselves Neglected, Precluded, or Surprized thereby; The Collector of this Treatise hath thought it very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the hastening of such Subscriptions, to cause, as well the Abstracts of the said Constitution and terms of Subscription, as of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:207630:10"/> the said Letters Patents, to be Printed and Published in these Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, [To the end all Persons into whose hands this shall come, may have the Contents thereof before them: And may apply themselves to make such Subscriptions as they shall think fit. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are to be Advertized, as they are hereby, that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribers of the first One Hundred and Fifty Thousand Pounds of the said Stock, will (for their Encouragement) have three <hi>per Cent.</hi> allowed them to be discounted out of their three first Quarterly Pavments; which is considerable.] Wherefore,</p>
               <p>Take next the Abstract of the said Constitution, Entituled, <hi>A Constitution, Model, or Frame and Method for Government and Mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Trade and Affairs of the Company of the Royal Fishery of</hi> England: As also of some Rules and Laws necessary to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Persons concerned in the Improvement of the Stock, <hi>&amp;c. viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">§. 1. That the Chief Government of the Company shall be in, and consist of a Governour, Sub-Governour, Deputy-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, and Twelve Committees, (whereof Four to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Directors, and Eight Masters) and also of Fifteen Assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, <hi>viz.</hi> To each of them, One. Also, Eight Wardens, and Five and Twenty Commissioners or Agents for <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and as many more of the other Members of the Company as shall from time to time be agreed to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Who, or any Fifteen or more of them, together with the Governour, Sub-Governour, Deputy-Governour, and their respective Assistants, or one of them to be present, Five or more of the Committees, Five or more of the Assistants, and Five or more of the other Members of the Company, are to have the Chief Power of making Laws, and Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole Affairs of the Company, in their General Court.</item>
                  <item n="2">§ 2. That the Court of Assistants consist of the Governour, Sub-Governour, Deputy-Governour, the Twelve Committees, and their Fifteen Assistants: Who, or any Seven or more of them (whereof the Governour, Sub-Governour, Deputy-Governour, or their respective Assistants, or one of them to be always one. Three of the said Committees, and Three of the said Assistants) are to have the chief Directing and Managing of the Affairs of the Company. And to Act in all things, according to such Rules, Orders, and Directions,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:207630:10"/> as shall from time to time be made and given by the said General Court: And for want of such, may do and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute all things, that they shall judge necessary and expedient, as the General Court may, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="3">§. 3. That for the more Distinct and Regular Management of the said Affairs, the said Court of Assistants are divided into four Chambers, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="1">1. The Fishery Chamber.</item>
                        <item n="2">2. The Stock or Store Chamber.</item>
                        <item n="3">3. The Treasury or Cash Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</item>
                        <item n="4">4. The Accompt Chamber.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>Each of which is to consist of the Governor, Sub-Governor, Deputy-Governor, and their respective As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistants, or one of them: One Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector and his Assistant: Two Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters and their Assistants, and two Wardens. Who, or any three or more of them to be a <hi>Quorum,</hi> are to Act and Execute by Rules and Instructions to be given to them under the Seal of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and not otherwise, in their several and respective Chambers.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item n="4">§. 4. That there be other Eight and Twenty Members of the Company, who shall be called Agents or Officers, and be employed in the said respective four Chambers, as they shall be directed by the Court of Assistants.</item>
                  <item n="5">§. 5. That the Nomination and Election of the Governor, Sub-Governor, Deputy-Governor, and Twelve Committees, shall be in and by the General Court Yearly: (Save that, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove five of them shall be removed in any one Year, but for just Causes exprest, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> The Eight Wardens and other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, Officers, or Commissioners for <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be Nominated by the Court of Assistants, or Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen of them.</item>
                  <item n="6">§. 6. That within Twenty Days after Publication of Subscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of One Hundred and Fifty Thousand Pounds, a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Court shall be called, for Electing a Sub-Governour or Deputy-Governour, and four Committees, by the New Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribers: And afterwards, Elections to be made on the Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth Day of <hi>November</hi> Yearly, wherein not above five Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees to be removed, as aforesaid.</item>
                  <item n="7">§. 7. The Articles, Terms, or Conditions, touching the Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Persons into the Company, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are confirmed, as a part of the Constitution, inviolably to be observed.</item>
                  <item n="8">§. 8. That all Subscribers who shall not be chosen for Managers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> shall be denominated as Traders or Adventurers: And their respective Shares, both as to Profit and Loss, Yearly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:207630:11"/> stated and determined, as other the Stock of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</item>
                  <item n="9">§. 9. That no Member of the Company after the Thirtieth day of <hi>November</hi> next, after Subscriptions are notified to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated, shall have any Vote in Elections, or making Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who shall not have Subscribed or be otherwise entituled to Five Hundred Pounds. Nor any Person be admitted a Member of the Court of Assistants, who shall not have Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed or be otherwise entituled to One Thousand Pounds.</item>
                  <item n="10">§. 10. One Tenth Part of the clear neat Profits is set apart for bearing the Charges of the Company, Court of Assistants, and four Chambers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Also to pay Sallaries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the Managing Members. Officers, and Servants. And the Distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions and Proportions of each are thereby setled, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So as that there shall be no Diminution of the Joynt-Stock on any Account whatsoever.</item>
                  <item n="11">§. 11. The Accompts of Profit and Loss are to be Yearly stated by the Officers in the Accompt Chamber; Each Year to end on the tenth of <hi>June;</hi> The Court of Assistants to Examine and Report the same to the General Court on the tenth of <hi>September</hi> following: Nine of them to Sign the Brief Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt thereof; and each ones share of Profits to be divided amongst the Persons concerned.</item>
                  <item n="12">§. 12. In case of Loss in any one Year, the Stock is to be made good out of the next, before any Dividend or Apportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Managers, Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Save that, Servants Sallaries of Thirty Pounds <hi>per Annum</hi> and under, may be advanced and re-imburs'd out of the next Years Profits: And in case the Profits of any first Years, shall not amount to One Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pounds each Share, the same shall also be made up out of the after-years Profits assigned for that purpose.</item>
                  <item n="13">§. 13. Mentions in what cases Persons may be dismist their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Employments: And that the General Court, or Court of Assistants Judgment shall be Final for the Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination thereof.</item>
                  <item n="14">§. 14. Sets the Fines on such as shall absent themselves from their Attendance, when Summoned, or upon Adjournments, or for not Attending so many hours as shall be agreed upon; Unless in case of Corporal Illness, or License from their respective Chambers.</item>
                  <item n="15">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:207630:11"/> §. 15. Directs the Custody of the Larger Seal, Letters Patents, Deeds and Evidences of Lands Granted to the Company, to be kept under two Locks, whereof the Governour, Sub-Governour, Deputy-Governour, and Directors to have the Keys of one, and their respective Assistants of the other. Also, that the Trustees, and each Chamber, the Secretary, and their respective Commissioners or Agents for <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to have one of the Lesser Seals, to be used by them respectively in the Company's Service.</item>
                  <item n="16">§. 16. If any Differences arise between the Members of the Court of Assistants or several Chambers, relating to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany's Affairs, they are to be determined by the General Court, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the refusers to submit thereto, to be dismist their Offices and Employments.</item>
                  <item n="17">§. 17. The Seven Trustees are named and settled; and three of the other Assistants. The other five Assistants are to be E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by them, out of such as shall become Subscribers to the New Stock of the Company. Their After-Nominations and Succession is also agreed to be, by and and amongst themselves, or the major part of the whole Fifteen Assistants.</item>
                  <item n="18">§. 18. The Governour, Sub-Governour, Deputy-Governour, Committees Assistants, and all Subscribers, before they be admitted into any Trust or Office in the Company, are to Declare their Approbation of and Acquiescing in the Constitution, and all other Constitutions, Laws, and Rules of the Company. As is more at large therein exprest.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Here also followeth the Abstract of the forementioned Articles, Terms, or Conditions, upon which all and singular Persons, of what Quality soever, within the Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. may be admitted into the Company of the Royal Fishery of <hi>England,</hi> or be Traders or Adventurers with them, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1. That whosoever shall Subscribe and Pay in any Sum or Sums of Money towards a Joynt-Stock for carrying on the Trade of the Company, shall be admitted into the same, and have and receive all the Benefits and Advantages thereof; subject to the Constitution, Laws, and Rules of the Company, and these Articles, Terms, and Conditions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="2">2. That the Sum designed to be at present Subscribed be Three Hundred Thousand Pounds, whereof One Hundred Thousand
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:207630:12"/> Pounds by the surviving Patentees, their Heirs and Assigns; and the other present Members of the Company. And Two Hundred Thousand Pounds more, by other Persons. The same to be paid into the Treasury of the said Company, in manner following, <hi>viz.</hi> The first Tenth Part thereof to be paid within Thirty Days from and after Notice or Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Compleating the Subscriptions of the said Three Hundred Thousand Pounds, or of One Hundred and Fifty Thousand Pounds at least, in part thereof. One Tenth Part more within three Months next after their respective First Payments: And the other remaining eight Tenth Parts, by eight equal next successive Quarterly Payments.</item>
                  <item n="3">3. That one Tenth Part of each Sum so Subscribed shall be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to and for the Use and Disposal of the Trustees, and of such Persons as they shall judge have heretofore been, or may hereafter be Useful for, or in Promoting the Interest and Service of the Company, without Accompt. So as the same nevertheless shall be and remain in the Stock, for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on the Trade thereof. And the remaining Nine Parts, to and for the sole Use and Benefit of the respective Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribers, their Executors, Administrators, and Assigns.</item>
                  <item n="4">4. That whatsoever further Sums shall, at any time hereafter, be thought fit by the Company to be Subscribed and Paid in, for increasing the said Stock, shall be in like manner subject to the Payment of the like Tenth Part, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For and towards the Re-imbursement of the Subscribers said Tenth Part of the said First Three Hundred Thousand Pounds.</item>
                  <item n="5">5. That whosoever shall Subscribe and pay in his First Payment, and shall not make his second, or any after-Payments, by the respective days or times before limited, shall forfeit his first Payment to the Use of the Company, and have Credit only for such After-Payments as he shall make.</item>
                  <item n="6">6. That all Shares or Sums amounting to Fifty Pounds, and As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signments thereof, shall be Enter'd and Register'd: And Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates thereof exemplified under the Seal, be given for the same, to such Persons as shall desire it.</item>
                  <item n="7">7. That no Person shall be hereafter admitted a Member of the Company, unless he shall, at the time of his Subscription, Declare his Approbation of and Submitting to these Articles, and engage himself to Observe and Keep the same inviolably. And also all such Constitutions, Laws, and Rules of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:207630:12"/> Company, as they have, or shall make, for the Management and Regulation of their Trade, pursuant to the Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and the present Constitution. As appears more at large therein.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And so much shall suffice for Answer of the First Particular proposed to be considered by the Collector hereof, <hi>viz.</hi> The Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of what Attempts have been made; Under what Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements; With what Stocks, and Successes, both for Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Caution.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>For the Second, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>How all Miscarriages in the said Fishery may be Remedied and Amended: And whence we may ground our Confidence, That in a due Management of the said Affair for the Future (as is Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by the said Company) they cannot miss of a desired Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect upon their undertaking it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1st,</hi> In order whereunto, the Collector hath thought fit to offer the perusal of a small Treatise, entituled, <hi>The Soveraignty of the British Seas,</hi> Proved by Records, History, and the Municipal Laws of this Kingdom. Written by Sir <hi>John Burroughs,</hi> Knight, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1633. and Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1651. Which being hard to be gotten, some few Pages thereof are thence transcribed. Being so much as the Author thereof hath Recommended under the Head or Title of, <hi>The Inestimable Riches and Commodities of the British Seas.</hi> Which are as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Coasts of <hi>Great Britain</hi> do yield such a continual Sea-Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest of Gain and Benefit to all those that with Diligence do La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the same, that no Time or Season in the Year passeth without some apparent means of Profitable Employment, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to such as apply themselves to Fishing: Which, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Year unto the latter end, continueth upon some part or other of our Coasts: And therein such infinite Sholes and Multitudes of Fishes are offered to the Takers, as may justly move Admiration, not only to Strangers, but to those that daily be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed among them.</p>
               <p>The Summer Fishing for Herrings beginneth about <hi>Midsummer,</hi> and lasteth some part of <hi>August.</hi> The Winter Fishing for Herrings lasteth from <hi>September</hi> to the middle of <hi>November.</hi> Both which extend in place from <hi>Boughones</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the <hi>Thames</hi> Mouth.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:207630:13"/>
               <p> The Fishing for Cod at <hi>Alamby, Whirlington,</hi> and <hi>Whitehaven,</hi> near the Coast of <hi>Lancashire,</hi> from <hi>Easter</hi> until <hi>Whitsontide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing for Hake at <hi>Aberdeine, Abveswhich,</hi> and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces between <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> from <hi>Whitsontide</hi> to St. <hi>James tide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing of Cod and Ling about <hi>Padstow</hi> within the Land, and of <hi>Severn,</hi> from <hi>Christmas</hi> to <hi>Mid-Lent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing for Cod on the West part of <hi>Ireland</hi> (frequented by those of <hi>Biscay, Galicia,</hi> and <hi>Portugal)</hi> from the beginning of <hi>April</hi> until the end of <hi>June.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing for Cod and Ling on the North and North-East of <hi>Ireland,</hi> from <hi>Christmas</hi> until <hi>Michaelmas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing for Pilchers on the West Coast of <hi>England,</hi> from St. <hi>James tide</hi> until <hi>Michaelmas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing for Cod and Ling upon the North-East of <hi>England,</hi> from <hi>Easter</hi> until <hi>Midsummer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing of Great Staple Ling, and many other sorts of Fish lying about the Islands of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and in the several Parts of the <hi>British</hi> Seas, all the Year long.</p>
               <p>In <hi>September,</hi> not many Years since, upon the Coast of <hi>Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> near <hi>Minigal,</hi> Five Hundred Tun of Fish were taken in one day: And about the same time, Three Thousand Pounds worth of Fish, in one day, were taken at St. <hi>Ives</hi> in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> by small Boats, and other poor Provisions.</p>
               <p>Our Five-Men-Boats and Cobles, adventuring in a Calm to Lanch out among the <hi>Holland</hi> Busses not far from <hi>Robin Hood</hi>'s Bay, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Whitby</hi> full Fraught with Herrings; and reported, that they saw some of those Busses take Ten, Twenty, Twenty four Lasts at a Draught of Herrings. And returned into their own Country with Forty, Fifty, and an Hundred Lasts of Herrings in one Buss.</p>
               <p>Our Fleet of Colliers, not many Years since, returning from <hi>Newcastle</hi> Laden with Coals, about the Well near <hi>Flanborrough-Head</hi> and <hi>Scarborrough,</hi> met with such multitude of Cods, Ling, and Herring, that one among the rest, with certain Sheep-hooks and other like Instruments, drew up as much Cod and Ling in a little space of time, as were Sold, well-near, for as much as her whole Lading of Coals. And many hundred of Ships might have been there Laden in two Days and two Nights.</p>
               <p>Out of which wonderful Affluence, and abundance of Fish swarming in our Seas, that we may the better perceive the Infinite Gain which Foreign Nations make; I will especially insist upon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:207630:13"/> the Fishing of the Hollanders in our Coasts, and thereby shew how by this means, principally they have Increased.</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1. In Shipping.</item>
                  <item n="2">2. In Marriners.</item>
                  <item n="3">3. In Trade.</item>
                  <item n="4">4. In Towns and Fortifications.</item>
                  <item n="5">5. In Power Externe or Abroad.</item>
                  <item n="6">6. In Publick Revenue.</item>
                  <item n="7">7. In Private Wealth.</item>
                  <item n="8">8. In all manner of Provisions, and Store of things necessary.</item>
               </list>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>First,</hi> Increase of Shipping.</head>
                  <p>Besides Seven Hundred Strand-boats, Four Hundred Evars, and Four Hundred Sullits, Drivers and Tod-boats, wherewith the Hollanders Fish upon their own Coasts; every one of these im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying another Ship to fetch Salt, and carry their Fish into other Countries; being in all Three Thousand Sail, Maintaining and Setting on work, at least Forty Thousand Persons, Fishers, Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Women and Children. They have One Hundred Dogger-Boats, of One Hundred and Fifty Tuns a piece, or thereabouts: Seaven Hundred Pincks and Well-Boats, from Sixty to One Hundred Tuns a piece; which altogether Fish upon the Coasts of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> for Cod and Ling only; and each of these imploy another Vessel for Providing of Salt, and Transporting of their Fish; making in all, One Thousand Six Hundred Ships; which maintain and imploy Persons of all sorts, Forty Thousand at least.</p>
                  <p>For the Herring Season, they have Sixteen Hundred Busses at the least, all of them Fishing only upon our Coasts, from <hi>Boug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honnes</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the mouth of the <hi>Thames.</hi> And every one of these maketh work for Three other Ships that attend her: The one to bring in Salt from Foreign Parts; another to carry the said Salt and Cask to the Busses, and to bring back their Herrings; and the Third to Transport the said Fish into Foreign Countries. So that the total Number of Ships and Busses plying the Herring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, is Six Thousand Four Hundred: Whereby every Buss, one with another, imployeth Forty Men Marriners and Fishers, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her own hold; and the rest Ten Men a piece; which amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:207630:14"/> to One Hundred and Twelve Thousand Fishers and Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: All which maintain double, if not treble so many Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Women and Children at Land.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, They have Four Hundred other Vessels, at least, that take Herring at <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> and there sell them for Ready Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. So that the Hollanders (besides Three Thousand Ships be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned, Fishing upon our own Shores) have at least Four Thousand Eight Hundred Ships, only maintained by the Seas of Great Britain; by which means principally, <hi>Holland</hi> being not so big as one of our Shires of <hi>England,</hi> (containing not above Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Eight Miles in Length, and Three in Breadth) have increased the number of their Shipping to at least Ten Thousand Sail; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more than are in <hi>England, France, Spain, Portugal, Italy, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, Poland, Sweden,</hi> and <hi>Rushia;</hi> and to this number they add every day: although their Country it self, affords them neither Materials, Victual, nor Merchandize to be accounted of, towards their setting forth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Increase of Marriners.</head>
                  <p>The Number of Ships Fishing on our Coasts being, as aforesaid, Eight Thousand Four Hundred; If we allow but Twenty Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to every Ship, one with another, the total of Marriners and Fishers amounteth to One Hundred Sixty Eight Thousand: Out of which Number they daily furnish their longer Voyages, to all parts of the World. For, by this means, they are not only enabled to Brook the Seas, and to know the use of the Tackles and Compass, but are likewise instructed in the Principles of Navigation and Pilotage; in so much as from hence, their greatest Navigators have their Education and Breeding.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Increase of Trade.</head>
                  <p>By reason of those multitude of Ships and Marriners, they have extended their Trade to all parts of the World; Exporting for the most part in all their Voyages, our Herrings and other Fish, for the maintenance of the same. In Exchange whereof they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn the several Commodities of other Countries, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From the Southern parts, as <hi>France, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Portugal;</hi> For
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:207630:14"/> our Herrings they return Oyles, Wines, Prunes, Honey, Wools, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With Store of Coyne in Specie.</p>
                  <p>From the <hi>Streights;</hi> Velvets, Sattins, and all sorts of Silks, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loms, Currans, Oyles, and all Grocery Wares, with much Money.</p>
                  <p>From the East Countries; For our Herrings, and other <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> Commodities before returned, they bring home Corne, Wax, Flax, Hemp, Pitch, Tar, Soap-ashes, Iron, Copper, Steel, Clap-board, Wainscot, Timber, Deal-boards, Dollers, and <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary Gilders.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From <hi>Germany;</hi> For Herrings and other Salt Fish; Iron, Steel, Glass, Mill-stones, Rhenish Wines, Button-plate for Armour, with other Munition; Silks, Velvets, Rashes, Fustians, Barratees, and such like <hi>Frankford</hi> Commodities; with store of Rix Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Brabrant,</hi> they return for the most part ready Money, with some Tapestries and Hul-shop. Yea, some of our Herrings are carried as far as <hi>Braseil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that which is more strange, and greatly to our Shame, they have Four Hundred Ships with Fish; which our Men of <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> within <hi>Kenn,</hi> almost at Land, do vent our Herrings amongst us here in <hi>England:</hi> And make us pay for the Fish taken upon our own Coasts, ready Money; wherewith they store their own Countrey.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Increase of Towns and Forts.</head>
                  <p>By this their large Extent of Trade, they are become, as it were, Citizens of the whole World; whereby they have so enlarged their Towns, that most of them, within these Four Hundred years, are full as great again as they were before. <hi>Amsterdam, Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and <hi>Middleborrough,</hi> having been lately twice inlarged; and their Streets and Buildings so fair and orderly set forth, That, for Beauty and Strength, they may compare with any other in the World: Upon which they bestow infinite Sums of Money: All originally flowing from the Bounty of the Sea. From whence, by their Labour and Industry, they derive the beginning of all that Wealth and Greatness; and particularly for the Havens of the aforesaid Towns: Whereof some of them cost Forty, Fifty, or an Hundred Thousand Pounds. Their Fortifications also, both
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:207630:15"/> for Number and Strength, upon which they have bestowed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Sums of Money, may Compare with any other what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Increase of Power Abroad.</head>
                  <p>Such being then the Number of the Ships and Marriners, and so great their Trade, occasioned principally by their Fishing, they have not only Strengthned and Fortified themselves at home, to repell all Forreign Invasion (as lately in the War between them and <hi>Spain)</hi> but have likewise stretch'd their Power into the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West Indies:</hi> In many Places whereof, they are Lords of the Sea-Coasts: And have likewise Fortified upon the Main, where the Kings and People are at their Devotion. And, more than this, all Neighbour Princes, in their Differences, by reason of this their Power at Sea, are glad to have them of their Party. So that, next to the English, they are now become the most redoubted Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at Sea, of any other whatsoever.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Increase of Publick Revenue,</head>
                  <p>Moreover, How mightily the Publick Revenue and Customs of that State are increased by their Fishing, may appear, in that, above Thirty years since, over and above the Customs of other Merchandize, Excises, Licenses, Waftage and Lastage, there was paid to the States, for Custom of Herring and other Salt Fish, above Three Hundred Thousand Pounds in One Year; Besides the Tenth Fish and Cask paid for Waftage; which cometh at the least, to as much more, among the <hi>Hollanders</hi> only: Whereto, the tenth of other Nations being added, it amounteth to a far greater Sum.</p>
                  <p>We are likewise to know, That great part of their Fish is sold in other Countries for ready Monies; for which they commonly Export of the finest Gold and Silver: And, coming home, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyne it of a baser Allay, under their own Stamp; which is not a small means to augment the Publick Treasure.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:207630:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Seaventhly,</hi> Increase of Private wealth.</head>
                  <p>As touching their Private Wealth; If we consider the abundant Store of Herrings and other Fish by them taken, and the usual Prices that they are Sold for; As also, The multitude of Trades-men and Artizans, that by reason of this their Fishing, are daily set on work; We must needs conclude, that the Gain thereof, made by Private Men, must, of necessity, be exceeding great, as by observing the Particulars following will plainly appear.</p>
                  <p>During the Wars between the King of <hi>Spain</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> before the last Truce, <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> by Taking, Spoyling, and Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Busses of <hi>Holland;</hi> and setting great Ransom upon their Fishermen, Inforced them to Compound for great Sums, that they might Fish quietly for one Year. Whereupon, the next year after, the Fishermen agreed among themselves to pay a Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler upon every Last of Herrings, towards the maintenance of certain Ships of War to Waft, and secure them in their Fishing: By reason whereof, there was a Record kept of the several Lasts of Herrings taken that year: And it appeared thereby, that in one half year, there were taken Three Hundred Thousand Lasts of Herrings; which at Twelve pound <hi>per</hi> Last, amounteth to Three Millions Six Hundred Thousand Pounds. And, at Sixteen, Twenty, Thirty Pounds the Last, they are ordinarily Sold, then Transported into other Countries, it cometh to at least Five Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions. Whereunto, if we add the Herrings taken by other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, together with the Cod, Ling, Hake, and the Fish taken by the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and other our Neighbours, upon the British Coasts all the year long, the total will evidently arise to be above Ten Millions.</p>
                  <p>The great Trade of Fishing employing so many Men and Ships at Sea, must likewise necessarily maintain as great a Number of Trades-men, and other Artizans on Land; as Spinners, and Hemp-winders to Cables, Cordage, Yarn-twine for Nets and Lines: Weavers to make Sayle Cloaths, Cecive-Packers, Tollers, Dres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers, and Couchers, to sort and make the Herring Lawful Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize: Tanners to Tann their Sails and Nets: Coopers to make Casks: Block and Bowl-makers for Ships: Keel-men, and Labourers for carrying and removing their Fish: Sawyers for Planks: Carpenters, Shipwrights, Smiths, Car-men, Boat-men,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:207630:16"/> Brewers, Bakers, and a Number of others, whereof many are maymed Persons, and unfit to be otherwise employed. Besides the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of all their several Wives, Children and Families. And further, every Man and Maid Servant, or Orphan, having a poor Stock, may venture the same in their Fishing Voyages; which affords them ordinarily a great Increase, and is duly paid, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the proportion of their Gain.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Eighthly,</hi> Increase of Provisions.</head>
                  <p>And, to conclude, It is manifest, that <hi>Holland,</hi> only affording it self some few Hops, Madder, Butter and Cheese, aboundeth notwithstanding (by reason of this Art of Fishing) in plentiful manner, with all kind of Provisions, as well for Life, as in Corne, Beef, Muttons, Hides and Clothes: as for Luxury, in Wines, Silks and Spices; and for Defence, as in Pitch, Tar, Cordage, Timber. All which they have, not only in competent proportion for their use, but are likewise able from their several Magazines to supply their Neighbour Countries.</p>
                  <p>The Premises considered, it maketh much to the Ignominy and Shame of our English Nation, That GOD and Nature offering us so great a Treasure, even at our own doors, we do notwithstanding neglect the Benefit thereof; and by paying Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to Strangers for the Fish of our own Seas, Impoverish our selves to make them Rich; in so much, that for want of Industry and Care in this particular, Two Hundred Twenty Five Fisher-Towns are decayed and reduced to extreme Poverty: Whereas on the contrary, by diligently endeavouring to make use of so great a Blessing, we might in short time regain these decayed Towns of the Kingdom, and add both Honour, Strength, and Riches to our King and Country: Which, how easily it may be done, will appear by some few Observations following.</p>
                  <p>By Erecting Two Hundred and Fifty Busses of reasonable Strength and Bigness, there will be employment made for a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Ships; and for at least Ten Thousand Fishermen and Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners at Sea; and consequently for as many Tradesmen and Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers at Land.</p>
                  <p>The Herrings taken by the Busses will afford his Majesty yearly Custom Outward, and for Commodities returned Inward, Thirty Thousand Pounds and above.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:207630:16"/>
                  <p> We have Timber sufficient, and at reasonable Rates growing in our own Kingdom for the Building of Busses. Every Shire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth hardy and able Men, fit for such Imployment, who now live poorly and idle at home.</p>
                  <p>We have Victuals in great Plenty, sold at easy Rates, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out payment of Excises or Impost.</p>
                  <p>Our Shores and Harbours are near the Places where the Fish do haunt.</p>
                  <p>For Drink or Nets, Salting and Packing our Fish, and for Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour in stress of Weather, we may bring our Fish to Land, Salt and Pack it: And from some parts of his Majesties Dominions, be at our Markets in <hi>France, Spain,</hi> or <hi>Italy,</hi> before the <hi>Hallander</hi> can arrive in <hi>Holland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We have means to Transport our Fishing into some Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Countries, where the <hi>Hollanders</hi> seldom or never come: And though we had as many Busses as the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> yet is there vent for all or more. For in the East and Northerne Countries, and in many other places, Herrings are every days meat, Winter and Summer; as well to draw on Drink, as to satisfie Hunger. And in most places, the greatest part of the year, they are scarce to be had: For presently after <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> the Sound and Rivers are Frozen up; so as no Herrings can be Transported into Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty several Kingdoms and Free States, until <hi>July;</hi> which is for Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Weeks space together: So that, when <hi>Lent</hi> comes, there are few to be bought for Money.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lastly,</hi> Since by Care and Industry we gained from the <hi>Flem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings,</hi> doubtless, so by the same means we may as easily grow ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in the Art of Fishing; and in time, make it a Staple Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of our own. But this we shall the better and sooner do, if we consider and endeavour to reform certain Wants and Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, which hitherto have hindered us from effecting that Good and Great Work; whereof, these that follow are none of the least.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>First,</hi> General Liberty of Eating Flesh, contrary to old Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoms, and the Statute Laws provided for observing Fish-days; from whence scarcity and Dearth of Fish proceedeth: For where Flesh is ordinarily spent, Fish will not be bought; and want of Sale decayeth all Trade; Gain being the Nurse of Industry.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Want of Order and Discretion in our Fishing: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man being left to himself, and permitted to Fish as best li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him; whereas, amongst the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> two of the best Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:207630:17"/> Fishermen, are appointed to Guide the rest of the Fleet; all others being bound to follow them, and to cast their Nets ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Direction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>Hollanders</hi> and other Nations, set forth with their Busses in <hi>June,</hi> to find the Shole of Fish, and having found it, dwell amongst it till <hi>November;</hi> whereas we stay till the Herring come home to our Road-steads, and sometimes suffer them to pass by, e're we look out; our Herring Fishing containing only Seven Weeks at the most, and theirs Twenty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The <hi>Hollanders</hi> Busses are great and strong, and able to Brook foul Weather: Whereas our Cobles, Crayers, and Boats, being small and thinsided, are easily swallowed up by a rough Sea; not daring to adventure far in fair weather, by reason of their weakness for fear of Stormes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The <hi>Hollanders</hi> are Industrious; and no sooner are dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of their Lading, but presently put forth for more, and seek for Markets abroad, as well as at home. Whereas, our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, after they have been once at Sea, do commonly never return again, until all the Money taken for their Fish be spent, and they in Debt: seeking only to serve the next Market.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The <hi>Hollanders</hi> have certain Merchants, who, during the Herring Season, do only come to the places where the Busses arrive, and, joyning together in several Companies, do present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agree for Thirty or Forty Busses at once: And so being dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, they may speedily return to their former Fishing. Whereas our Fishermen are uncertain of their Chapmen, and forced to spend much time in putting off their Fish by Parcels.</p>
                  <p>These and other Defects would carefully be taken into conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and certain Orders made, to make our Fishing Prosperous and Successful: especially considering the fearful mischiefs, the neglects hereof, hath brought to the King and Kingdom in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; and to many good Towns and Corporations in particular; as by Authority (even of Parliament it self, in the Statute of 33 <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII.) is plainly testified, which I have summarily here set down to avoid the Prolixity of the Original. <hi>Viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Because the <hi>English</hi> Fishermen Dwelling on the Sea Coasts, did leave off their Trade of Fishing in our Seas, and went the Half-Seas over, and there, upon the Seas, did buy Fish of the <hi>Pickards, Flemmings, Normans,</hi> and <hi>Zealanders:</hi> By reason where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, many incommodities did grow to the Realm; <hi>viz.</hi> The decay of the Wealth and Prosperity, as well of the Cinque-Ports
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:207630:17"/> and Members of the same, as of other Coast-Towns by the Sea-side, which were Builded and Inhabited by great Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of People, by reason of using and exercising the Craft and Feat of Fishing. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Decay of a great number of Boats and Ships. And, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The decay of many good Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, both able in Body by their Diligence, Labour, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Exercise of Fishing; and Expert, by reason thereof, in the Knowledge of the Sea-Coasts, as well within this Realm, as in other parts beyond the Seas. It was therefore Enacted, That no manner of Persons, <hi>English,</hi> Denizens, or Strangers at that time, or any time after, dwelling in <hi>England,</hi> should buy any Fish of any Strangers in the said Ports of <hi>Flanders, Zealand, Piccardie, France;</hi> or upon the Sea between Shore and Shore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q> Which Act, by many continuations was continued from Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Parliament, until the first of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and from thence to the end of the next Parliament, and then expired.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>Conclusion.</hi> Seeing by that which hath formerly been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, it evidently appeareth, That the Kings of <hi>England</hi> (by Immemorable Prescription, continual Usage and Possession, the acknowledgment of all our Neighbour States, and the Municipal Laws of the Kingdom) have ever held the Soveraign Lordship of the Seas of <hi>England;</hi> and that unto his Majesty, by reason of his Soveraignty, the supreme Command and Jurisdiction over the Passage and Fishing in the same rightfully appertaineth: Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring also, the natural Scyte of those our Seas that interpose them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves between the great Nothern Commerce of that of the whole World, and that of the East, West, and Southern Climates: And withal, the infinite Commodities that by Fishing in the same is daily made; it cannot be doubted, but his Majesty, by means of his own Excellent Wisdom and Virtue; and by the Industry of his Faithful Subjects and People, may easily, without injustice to any Prince or Person whatsoever, be made the greatest Monarch for Command and Wealth; and his People the most Opulent and Flourishing Nation, of any other in the World. And this the rather, for that his Majesty is now absolute Commander of the British Isle; and hath also inlarged his Dominions over a great part of the Western <hi>Indies:</hi> By means of which extent of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, (crossing in a manner the whole Ocean) the Trade and Persons of all Nations (removing from one part of the World, to the other) must of necessity, first or last, come within the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass of his Power and Jurisdiction.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:207630:18"/>
                  <p> And therefore, the Soveraignty of our Seas being the most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Jewel of his Majesties Crown, and (next, under God) the principal means of our Wealth and Safety; <hi>All true</hi> English <hi>Hearts and Hands are bound, by all possible means and diligence to preserve and maintain the same, even with the utmost of their Lives, their Goods, and Fortunes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus far the Author of that incomparable Treatise, on that Head, <hi>viz.</hi> Of the inestimable Riches and Commodities of the British Seas.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the next Place.</head>
               <p>The Collector hereof conceives it useful to Transcribe and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish some of Sir <hi>Walter Raleighs</hi> Observations touching Trade and Commerce with the <hi>Hollander</hi> and other Nations: Proving, That our Sea and Land Commodities, enrich and strengthen other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries against our own; which he humbly Presented to his Majesty King <hi>James</hi> I. <hi>Anno</hi> 1618. in the words following: <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>May it please your Majesty to consider these Points following.</q>
               <p n="1">1. Whether it be not fit, That a State-Merchant be settled within your Dominions, which may both dispose more profitably of the Riches thereof: and incounter Policies of Merchant Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, who now go beyond us in all kind of profitable Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether it be not necessary, That your Native Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties should receive their full Manufactory by your Subjects, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Dominions.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether it be not fit, the Coals should yield your Majesty and Subjects a better value, by permitting them to pass out of the Land; and that they be in your Subjects Shipping only Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sported.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether it be not fit, your Majesty presently raise your Coyn to as high Rates, as it is in the parts beyond the Sea.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether it be not necessary, That the great Sea-business of Fishing be forthwith set forwards.</p>
               <p>If it please your Majesty to approve of these Considerations, and accordingly to put them in a right course of Execution; I assure my self, by God's Help, in short time your Majesty's Customs, and the continual coming into your Coffers, will be exceedingly increased; your Ships and Marriners trebled; your Land and wast Towns, which are now out of Gates, better Replenished;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:207630:18"/> and your People Imployed, to the great Enriching and Honour of your Kingdom; with the Applause and to the Comfort of your Loyal Subjects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Touching Fishing.</head>
               <p>The great Sea-business of Fishing doth imploy near Twenty Thousand Ships and Vessels; and four Hundred Thousand Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are employed thereby yearly, upon your Coasts of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> with Sixty Ships of War, which may prove dangerous.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> only, have about Three Thousand Ships to Fish withal, and Fifty Thousand People are employed yearly by them upon your Majesty's Coasts of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> These Three Thousand Fishing Ships and Vessels of the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> do employ near Nine Thousand other Ships and Vessels; and One Hundred and Fifty Thousand Persons more by Sea and Land, to make Provisions, to Dress and Transport the Fish they take, and return Commodities; whereby they are enabled, and do build yearly a Thousand Ships and Vessels, having not One Timber-tree growing in their own Countrey, nor home-bred Commodities to Lade One Hundred Ships; and yet they have Twenty Thousand Ships and Vessels, and all employed.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> VII. desirous to make his Kingdoms Powerful and Rich, by increase of Ships and Marriners, and Employment of his People, sent unto his Sea-Coast Towns, moving them to set up the Great and Rich Fishing; with promise to give them need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Privileges, and to furnish them with Loanes of Money, if need were, to incourage them; Yet his People were slack.</p>
               <p>Now, Since I have traced this business, and made my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours known to your Majesty, your Noble Men, Able Merchants and others, who have set down under their Hands for more Assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and promised to disburse large Sums of Money, for the building up of a Strong, Rich, and Large Sea-City; which will increase more Strength to your Land, give more Comfort, and do more Good to all your Cities and Towns than all the Companies of your Kingdoms, having fit and needful Privileges for the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding and strengthning of so weighty and needful a Business.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:207630:19"/>
               <p> For Example, Twenty Busses Built and put into a Sea-Coast Town, (where there is not one Ship before) there must be to carry, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, Transport, and make Provision for each Buss, three Ships: Likewise, every Ship setting on work Thirty several Trades and Occupations: and Four Thousand Persons by Sea and Land; in so much, as Three Hundred Persons are not able to make One Fleet of Nets in Four Months for the Busses; which is no small employment.</p>
               <p>Thus, By Twenty Busses are set on Work Eight Thousand Persons by Sea and Land, and an Increase of above One Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Marriners, and a Fleet of Eighty Sail of Ships, to belong to One Town, where none were before, to take the Wealth out of the Sea, and to enrich and strengthen the Land, only by raising Twenty Busses. Then, what good One Thousand or Two Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand will do, I leave to your Majesties Consideration.</p>
               <p>It is worthy to be noted, How necessary Fishermen are to the Common-wealth; and how needful to be Advanced and Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished. <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1. For taking God's Blessing out of the Sea to enrich the Realm, which otherwise we lose.</item>
                  <item n="2">2. For setting the People on Work.</item>
                  <item n="3">3. For making Plenty and Cheapness in the Realm.</item>
                  <item n="4">4. For encreasing of Ships to make the Land Powerful.</item>
                  <item n="5">5. For a continual Nursery, for Breeding and Increasing our Marriners.</item>
                  <item n="6">6. For making imployment of all sorts of People; as Blind, Lame, and Others, by Sea and Land; from Ten or Twelve years and upwards.</item>
                  <item n="7">7. For Enriching your Majesties Coffers, for Merchandizes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from other Countries, for Fish and Herrings.</item>
                  <item n="8">8. For the Encrease and Enabling of Merchants; which now droop, and daily decay.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Furthermore. <hi>Some Particulars needful to be Considered of, viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The mighty huge Fishing that ever could be heard of in the World, is upon the Coasts of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> But the great Fishery is in the Low Countries, and other Petty States, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they serve themselves, and all Christendom, as it shall appear.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:207630:19"/>
               <p> In Four Towns in the East Kingdoms, within the Sound <hi>(Quins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borrough, Elbing, Statten,</hi> and <hi>Dantzick)</hi> there are carried and vent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Year, between Thirty and Forty thousand Lasts of Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings; which, sold but at Fifteen or Sixteen Pounds the Last, is about Six hundred and twenty thousand pounds; And we none.</p>
               <p>Besides, <hi>Denmark, Norway, Sweathen, Leafland, Rye, Nevil,</hi> the <hi>Nerve,</hi> and other Port-Towns within the <hi>Sound,</hi> there is carried and vented above Ten thousand Lasts of Herrings, sold at Fifteen or Sixteen pounds the Last, is One hundred and seaventy thousand pounds more yearly. And, in such request are our Herrings there, that they are often sold for Twenty, Four and twenty, Thirty, and Thirty six pounds the Last; and we send not One Barrel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all those East Countries.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> send into <hi>Rushia</hi> near Fifteen hundred Lasts of Herrings, sold for about Thirty Shillings the Barrel, which amounts to Twenty seaven thousand Pounds; and we but about Twenty or Thirty Lasts.</p>
               <p>To <hi>Stoad, Hamborrough, Bremen, Embden</hi> upon the River of <hi>Elve, Weaser</hi> and <hi>Emby,</hi> are carried and vented of Fish and Herrings, about Six thousand Lasts, sold about Fifteen or Sixteen Pounds the Last, which is about One hundred thousand Pounds; and we none.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cleaveland, Gulickland,</hi> up the River of <hi>Rhine</hi> to <hi>Cullen, Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> or the <hi>Mayne,</hi> and so over all <hi>Germany</hi> is carried and vented Fish and Herrings near Two and twenty thousand Lasts, sold at Twenty Pounds the Last, which is Four hundred and forty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Pounds; and we none.</p>
               <p>Up the River of <hi>Maze, Leigh, Mastrich, Dendlow, Sutphin, Diventer, Camben, Swoole,</hi> and all over <hi>Lakeland,</hi> is carried and vented Seaven thousand Lasts of Herrings, sold at Twenty Pounds the Last, which comes to One hundred and forty thousand Pounds; and we none.</p>
               <p>To <hi>Gilderland, Artois, Henault, Brabant, Flanders,</hi> up the River of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> all over the Arch-Duke's Countrey, are carried and vented between Eight and Nine thousand Lasts, sold at Eighteen Pounds the Last, which is One hundred sixty two thousand Pounds; and we none.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> and Others, carryed of all sorts of Herrings to <hi>Roan</hi> only, in one year, besides all other parts of <hi>France,</hi> Fifty thousand Lasts of Herrings, sold at Twenty Pounds the Last, which is One million of Pounds; and we not One hundred Lasts
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:207630:20"/> thither. They are sold oftentimes for Twenty four, and Thirty Pounds the Last.</p>
               <p>Between <hi>Christmas</hi> and <hi>Lent,</hi> the Duties for Fish and Herrings came to Fifteen thousand Crowns, at <hi>Roan</hi> only. That year the late Queen Deceased; Sir <hi>Thomas Parry</hi> was Agent then there; and <hi>S. Savors</hi> his Man knows it to be true, who handled the busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, for pulling down the Impositions. Then, what great sums of Money came to all in the Port-Towns, to enrich the <hi>French</hi> King's Coffers, and to all the Kings and States throughout Christendom, to enrich their Coffers.</p>
               <p>Besides, The great quantity vented to the <hi>Streights,</hi> and the multitude spent in the Low Countries, which there is likewise sold for many a Hundred thousand Pounds more yearly, is neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to be remembred; and the Stream to be turned to the good of this Kingdom; to whose Sea-Coasts God only hath sent and given these great Blessings, and multitude of Riches for us to take, howsoever it hath been neglected to the hurt of this Kingdom; that any Nation should carry away out of this Kingdom yearly great Masses of Money for Fish taken in our Seas, and sold again by them to us; which must needs be a great Dishonour to our Nation, and hinderance to this Realm.</p>
               <p>In a word, The main Bulk and Mass of Herrings, from whence they raise so many Millions yearly, that enrich other Kingdoms, Kings and States Coffers, and likewise their own People; proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from our Seas and Lands: And the return of the Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Coyn they bring home in Exchange of Fish and other Commodities are so huge, as would require a large Discourse apart. And all the amends they make us, is, they beat us out of Trade in all Parts, <hi>with our own Commodities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. It is also thought meet here to Publish an Extract out of a Book Printed in <hi>Holland, Anno</hi> 1669. Put out by the late Pensionary <hi>John De Witt,</hi> entituled, <hi>A Representation of the wholsome Political Grounds and Maxims of the Republick of</hi> Holland, <hi>and</hi> West Fries<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. Wherein</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>He makes an estimate of the Number of Souls Subjects of the States General, and concludes they are in Number.</cell>
                        <cell>2,400,000.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>And says, these Persons maintain themselves as followeth. <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:207630:20"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>By Fishing at Sea, and to set them out as Fishers with Ships, Rigging, Casks, Salt and other Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials or Instruments, and the Traffick that depends thereon.</cell>
                        <cell>450,000.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>By Land Husbandry, In-land Fishing, Mowers of Downs, and Turff-makers, with those that are to furnish those Trades, with all sorts of Materials, as they are Husbandmen.</cell>
                        <cell>200,000.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>By making all manner of Manufactories, Ships, Mechanick, or Handycraft-works, which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed in Foreign Parts; as also, Traders relaing to the said Manufactures.</cell>
                        <cell>650,000.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>By Navigation, or Sailing for Freight and Trade only, whereby I mean Freight or Carriage into Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Parts, to Sell and to Buy: As also, to carry from and to <hi>Holland,</hi> all such Wares and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes, which pertain not to Fishing and Manufactures, nor depend thereon: And Lastly, I include herein all Inhabitants that are serviceable to such Traders and Owners of Ships let out to Freight, amounting in all to</cell>
                        <cell>250,000.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>By all these Inhabitants, as they are Men, Women, and Children, to provide with and work about all that is spent in this Land: as Meat, Drink, Cloathing, Housing; Arts necessary for Ease, Pleasure, or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament; Houshold Goods to sell or make.</cell>
                        <cell>650,000.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>By the Labour and Care of all the above-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Persons, Idle Gentry without Callings, Rulers and Officers in Politie, Usurers, Soldiers, Hospital-men, Beggars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>200,000.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>In all</cell>
                        <cell>2,400,000.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:207630:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That <hi>Holland</hi> lies very Commodiously to fetch its Provisions out of the Sea, and to Provide for its Maintenance by other Arts and Expedients; and how great a means of Subsistance the Fishery may tend to us.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>TO procure its Food out of the Sea, which is common to all Men, <hi>Holland</hi> is very well situate; not only on a Sea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding with great store of Fish near the <hi>Dogger-Sand,</hi> where Haddock, Cod, and Ling, may in great abundance be taken and salted: But also, near the Herring Fishery, which is no where else but on the Coast of <hi>Great Britain, viz.</hi> from St. <hi>Johns</hi> to St. <hi>James</hi>'s, about <hi>Hitland, Phagril</hi> and <hi>Bohennes</hi> in the deep Waters, Eastward of <hi>Yarmouth.</hi> And this Herring Fishing, now of Two hundred years standing, since <hi>William Benkelson</hi> learned first to Gill, Salt, and Pack them up in Casks, with the Cod Fishery, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come so effectual a means of Subsistance for these Lands, (especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally since so many Neighbouring People, by reason of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, are obliged upon certain Days and Weeks of the Year, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to refrain eating of Flesh) That the <hi>Hollanders</hi> do only Fish in a time of Peace with more than One thousand Busses, from Four and twenty to Thirty Lasts burthen each: and with One hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and seaventy small Vessels Fish for Herrings, within the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of <hi>Texell.</hi> So that those Thousand Ships being set to Sea for a Year, wherein they make Three Voyages, do cost above Ten millions of Gilders, accounting only the Buss with its Tackle at Four thousand five hundred and fifty Gilders; and the setting forth to Sea, Five thousand five hundred Gilders; there remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing of all its Preparation the Second Year, but the bare Vessel; and that much worne and torne, and needing great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration.</p>
               <p>If these Thousand Busses do take yearly at least Forty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Lasts of Herrings, counting them worth Two hundred Gilders the Last, they will produce to <hi>Holland</hi> more than Eight millions of Gilders.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:207630:21"/>
               <p> And seeing People have begun of late to make use of Whale-Oyl and Whale-Finns, and that they are taken to the Northward, not far from us, so that we by Southerly Winds can Sail thither in Six or Eight days, the Trade of Fisheries and Salt may easily be settled and fixed to us; or, as it were intailed to our Countrey, For to fix these Fisheries and many Manufactures, and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Trade and Returns of them, depending upon the Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Freighting of Ships; we must well consider, that the greatest difficulty to inable so innumerable a number of People to subsist of its own bottom, is the powerfullest means to draw all Foreign Wares into <hi>Holland:</hi> Not only to store them up there, and afterwards to send them up the Countries through the <hi>Mase, Waal, Yssel</hi> and the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> (making together one River) to numerous Towns and People lying on the side of them, (the most conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the World, for the Consumption of Goods) but also, to consume the said Imported Goods, or to have them wrought up at home. It being well known, that no Countrey in the World, of so small a Compass, has so many People and Master-workmen as we have. And besides this,</p>
               <p>Hereunto may be added, That no Countrey in the World, is so wonderfully trench'd or cut through for Navigable Rivers, whereby all Merchandize may be carried to and fro, with so little charge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Emanuel Van Materan,</hi> in his History says, <q>That in Three days time, <hi>Anno</hi> 1601. There Sailed out of <hi>Holland</hi> to the East<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Eight or Nine hundred Ships, and Fifteen hundred Busses, on Herring Fishing.</q> And, that Fishing is such, if that may be credited which the <hi>English</hi> Authors have written, <hi>[viz. Gerard Malines</hi> in his <hi>Lex Mercatoria,</hi> and Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> and which <hi>Lieven Van Aitzma, Anno</hi> 1653. <hi>p.</hi> 863. seems, in some measure to confirm] <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <q>That there are yearly taken and spent by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> above Three hundred thousand Lasts of Herrings, and other salted Fish:</q> And, That the Whale Fishing takes up above Twelve thousand Men, which Sail out of these Countries. For since the <hi>Greenland</hi> Company is Dissolved, and the Whale Fishing set open for all Men, that Fishing is increased from One to Ten; So that we compute, that all these Fishing Vessels are Built here; the Ropes, Sails, Nets, and Casks made here and provided with Salt: One may easily imagine, that there must be an incredible number of People that maintain themselves thereby; especially when we add thereunto, that all the People have need of Meat,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:207630:22"/> Drink, Cloathing and Housing; as also, that the Fish when caught, is Transported by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> by Shipping, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole World.</p>
               <p>And indeed, if it be true, that Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh</hi> affirms, (who made diligent scrutiny thereinto, in the year 1618. whereby to inform King <hi>James)</hi> That the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Fished on the Coast of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> with no less than Three Thousand Ships, and Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Thousand Men: And that they employed and set out to Sea, both to Transport and Sell the Fish so taken, and to make returns thereof, Nine thousand Ships more, and One hundred and fifty thousand Men besides. And if we hereunto add what he farther says, <hi>viz.</hi> That Twenty Busses do maintain Eight thousand Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: And that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> had in all, no less than Twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Ships at Sea.</p>
               <p>As also, That the Fisheries Navigation and Traffick by Sea, with its Dependencies since that time, to the year 1667. is increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed one third more: I say, if it be so, we may then easily conclude, That the Sea is a special means of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Subsistance; see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Holland,</hi> by this only way, affords by its own Industry, above Three hundred thousand Lasts of Salted Fish taken on board Ships. So that</p>
               <p>If we add hereunto the Whale, Oyl and Fins, and our <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Manufactures; with that which all our Rivers within our Dominions afford us, it must be confessed, That no Countrey in the World can make so many Ships lading of Merchandize out of its self, as <hi>Holland</hi> alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To which the Collector thinks he has the freedom to add,</hi> viz.</p>
               <p>That the Foundation of all this is, the Fish taken out of the <hi>British</hi> Seas, belonging to <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Take a Copy of some farther Considerations, in all humble<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ness propounded to his late Majesty King <hi>Charles</hi> II. by Dr. <hi>Benjamin Worsley,</hi> sometime Secretary to the Right Honourable the Lords of his said Majesties Council for Plantations and Trade, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which said Copy hath come to the hands of the Publisher, who well knew him to be a Person of great ingenuity and truth; and had spent some years and Hundreds of Pounds, in making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self master of this Craft, by his Travels into <hi>Holland,</hi> &amp;c. wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the Acceptance of all Persons, who incline to be concerned in the Fishery Affairs. He Asserts,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:207630:22"/> 1. That the least valuation that hath been hitherto generally put upon the Herring Fishing, is, Three millions of Pounds Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, <hi>per</hi> year.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the reasonableness of this valuation may appear, by the number of Busses usually imployed in the said Fishing, which are said to be at least Sixteen hundred; By the quantity of Fish usually caught in each of the said Busses; By the Registries kept of Import and Export of the said Fish in several Custom-houses of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Friezland;</hi> And by the known Price that the said Fish usually bears in all Markets.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That, according to this valuation, the Fishing alone doth amount to more than Either the whole Manufacture and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of <hi>England</hi> apart; Or the whole Manufacture of <hi>France</hi> apart; and consequently to more than the whole Plate and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Production of <hi>Spain,</hi> considered apart.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That the Fishing therefore being added to all the rest of the Manufactures of <hi>Holland,</hi> (both Woollen and Linnen) and to the greatness of its <hi>East India</hi> Trade, doth unavoidably cast a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-ballance upon <hi>Holland,</hi> more than upon any State of <hi>Europe</hi> besides: even near to the double, and by this means a Super-ballance also of Stock and Strength at Sea proportionably.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That on the other hand, If the scale of the said Fishing may by any means possibly be removed from <hi>Holland,</hi> and Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd into any other Nation; the Fishing so Transferr'd shall and must cast near as great an over-ballance of Trade upon that Nation, wherein it is, and as great an advantage of Stock, Commerce and Strength at Sea, as <hi>Holland</hi> it self now hath.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That the Fishing (then) is the very Goal or Prize of Trade, and the very Goal or Prize of the Dominion of the Sea; and that thing Singly, which whosoever gains, makes himself Master of both these: And that very thing, which, whosoever misseth, doth miss of both these.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That, If we shall therefore wholly relinquish the said Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Hollander,</hi> with all the Gain and Advantage of it, we shall and must relinquish (of course) to him, both the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority of Trade, and the Superiority of the Power at Sea. Yea, we shall and must also deprive our selves of all Capacity for ever, to hinder him in either of these Two: both because of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme loss we have had of our Seamen of late; and because we have neither any Moral, or Rational way, or Possibility left us, of recovering the said Loss again, unless by setting upon the said Fishery.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:207630:23"/> 8. That the Herring Fishing, though proper only to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty's Dominions, and though frequently attempted by us, hath nevertheless, hitherto, always miscarried with us, even from the very end that hath been propounded to our selves in it: Which is, the Example of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and the Gain he makes of it; and the necessity we suppose there is of following the same Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod which we observe him to take in it; which is, to catch and save the said Fish in Herring-Busses.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That this our Miscarriage constantly in it, hath produced, not only a General Indisposition, but a General Despondency up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Nation, any more to undertake it, or adventure upon it; as having entertained a certain secret Perswasion at length, through our unsuccessfulness in it, That our Nation hath not a Genius for it; and that there is a Mystery in it, which though the <hi>Dutch</hi> do well understand, yet we cannot reach it.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Whereas indeed the proper causes of all our Miscarriages, hath (as I humbly conceive) been rather produced from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencies following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1. Because we have not throughly considered, That the <hi>Dutch</hi> have many more Conveniencies for prosecuting the said Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing than we can possibly have, if we will make <hi>London</hi> to be the Principal Scale, Seat, or Staple for the said Fishing Trade (as hitherto we have done) and shall Resolve to bring all the Fish that is caught, here, into the <hi>Thames,</hi> to be Ship'd off hence; even as the <hi>Dutch</hi> do usually bring theirs into <hi>Holland,</hi> before it can be any where Transported. And therefore,</item>
                  <item n="2">2. Have not well weighed the great disadvantage of this very Foundation it self; in regard, it is not a matter of Election that the <hi>Dutch</hi> do bring in all their Herring first into <hi>Holland,</hi> before it be Ship'd, but is a matter of absolute Necessity that lyeth unavoidably on them, rather than of Choice.</item>
                  <item n="3">3. For as much as the <hi>Hollanders</hi> have now for near a whole Age been Masters of the said Fishing, and of the present Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of it, in managing it by Busses: And for as much as they have been now for so long a time possest of such a vast Stock, both of Busses, Boats, Nets, and all manner of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions and Conveniencies for it, which no other Nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides hath; and which none can in any reasonable time, nor without the Expence of at least a Million of Pounds <hi>Sterling</hi> ever be able to compass. They must, for these Reasons, of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:207630:23"/> necessity be in a capacity of Husbanding the said Fishery in the present Order of it, to a far greater degree of Advantage, than it is possible for any Nation to do besides, who shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour only to follow them, and imitate them in their way, and in the present manner of their Ordering of it.</item>
                  <item n="4">4. It seems not to have been duly considered, That the Fishing hath not only of late, but for many Years been made the very Interest of the <hi>Netherland</hi> State; and been look'd upon by them as such an Interest, without which it is every way impossible that they should be able to uphold the greatness of their Stock, Power, or Trade. And</item>
                  <item n="5">5. Such an Interest therefore, that, as they will never suffer themselves to be beaten or treated out of it, either by Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence or Force, so, never suffer any to share with them in it, if they can any way possibly hinder or avoid it. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently,</item>
                  <item n="6">6. That in as much as this is such an Interest as upon which they themselves know, that the whole of their Stock, Power, Strength, and Commerce by Sea, doth not only in part, but altogether depend; They must bend the chief of their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, Counsel, and Force, not only to discourage any that shall Attempt it, but utterly to beat out any that shall Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it; even though it should be with never so much loss to themselves for a season.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="11">11. That, as it is for these Causes, and upon these Grounds therefore, that we have hitherto lost all the Stock that we have ever employed about the said Fishing: So, while the said Causes and Grounds do remain, it seems altogether impossible that we should avoid the losing of whatever Stock we shall hereafter Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture in it, or Employ about it. Seeing, if we shall proceed in no other Method than that we have hitherto accustomed our selves to, it will always be in the Power of the <hi>Hollander</hi> to under-sell us: And he will be sure purposely to Anticipate, clog, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Market of us, where we shall Trade for the said Fish. Provided, we continue only in his course, and set not upon the said Fishing in any other better or more advantageous Order than that which he is himself so very well seen, vers'd, and experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in.</p>
               <p n="12">12. That by reason of the many Advantages which it is known that the <hi>Hollander</hi> hath of us in this Business: And by reason of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:207630:24"/> the Experience which we have so often had of our own loss and miscarriage in the said Fishing, we come likewise to lye under this further Disadvantage at present, <hi>viz.</hi> That there can be no ground rationally to expect that any Sock should for the future ever again be raised to set on foot the said Fishing, out of the voluntary Contribution of Ordinary and Private Persons.</p>
               <p n="13">13. That these things being thus truly stated, these Deductions following seem necessarily consequent.</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1. That it is altogether in vain ever to expect any Advantage from the said Fishing, unless some course can rationally be propounded, whereby we may set upon the said Fishing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that Extraordinary Preparation and Charge which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> are necessarily put unto at present in it. Nor, without we can be able to make the said Fish cheaper than the <hi>Hollander</hi> now does in the way wherein he is. Nor, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less we can be able to under-sell him something in it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any considerable Loss to our selves. Nor, without we can also hope (upon such Grounds and Inductions as are reasonable) that we shall be able to go to Market with the said Fish before him.</item>
                  <item n="2">2. That the setting also upon the said Fishery seems wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practical, if not impossible, unless such a Stock may be raised and found out for it, that shall not be dependant upon the Subscriptions or Pleasures of any Private Persons: And that shall nevertheless be, not only sufficient to begin it, but suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient also by being applyed constantly to it by degrees to promote it: And may be sufficient also, in time, with the Blessing of God upon it, Both to Defend it, and Protect it; and therefore to bear the Hazard of such extraordinary Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sualties in it, which is not to be expected can, or ever will be born by the Fortune of Private Persons.</item>
                  <item n="3">3. That the said Fishing, being so great an Interest of State, as it is in <hi>Holland,</hi> it can never increase therefore with any Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess in these Kingdoms, but it must expect to meet with many Indignities, Discouragements, and Affronts to be put upon it, from our Neighbours, in order to hinder it: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it can never be so far pursued in <hi>England,</hi> as to arive to any visible Head, and much less to attain to any manner of Growth or Completion, without the Express Authority of the Government to Countenance it, and without the thorough
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:207630:24"/> Resolution of His Majesty to Defend it, and Protect it, in the Just and Merchantable Methods of it.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="14">14. Which Foundations, as those which are the Main and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal ones, being now Premised, for the full, clear, and entire setling of the whole Affair of the Fishery, These Particulars fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, are therefore in all Humbleness, supposed to be requisite.</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1">1. The Signal and Express Countenance of His Majesty in it, with the Publick Authority of Parliament.</item>
                  <item n="2">2. A Correspondency through His Majesty's Special Favour, Assistance, and Grace, with the Government and Subjects of His Majesty's Kingdoms of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item n="3">3. An exact Method for pursuing of the said Fishery in such manner as may not only be easie, seizable, and practical, but as secure, and free from all Hazards, as we can Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally or Morally propound things to be.</item>
                  <item n="4">4. Such a different manner and order of Catching, Curing, and Saving the said Fish, as shall be every way more cheap, than that which the <hi>Hollander</hi> is in the present Practice of, and such as may be soon expedited and dispatched also, as that the Foreign Markets of the <hi>Hollander</hi> shall be generally always anticipated by our Shipping.</item>
                  <item n="5">5. Such a Body of Instructions therefore as shall be sufficient to give light into each Particular that may rationally be suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to be of moment with reference to the whole Affair of the said Fishing.</item>
                  <item n="6">6. A select Choice of such Persons, as a Council or Directors of the said Fishing (not exceeding seven) as may not only be of Integrity, but of sufficient Ability to manage all things tending to the Promoting of the said Fishery, pursuant to the said Method and Instructions that shall be propounded: And consequently such Persons as are skilled in the Practical part of the Trade of the said Fishing.</item>
                  <item n="7">7. That the said Council or Directors have the same Powers and Authorities given them, as have been usually heretofore granted to such Councils, as have been appointed for the Royal Fishing, together with such other Powers as to the Wisdom of His Majesty shall be thought fit: And that the said Powers and Authorities be confirmed by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. And</item>
                  <item n="8">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:207630:25"/> 8. That Grand Commissioners be also appointed, for the chief Over-sight of the said Fishing, consisting of the Principal Officers of State, and of so many others, as to the Wisdom of His Majesty, and of the Parliament shall be thought fit.</item>
                  <item n="9">9. That the said Grand Commissioners have full Power to call the said Council or Directors of the said Fishery to an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, once every half Year; and to see by the Entries of their Journal, Letters, Orders, and Instructions, what Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress they do from time to time make in the said Business. To the end that His Majesty may have a perfect Account of it, and their Faithfulness or Negligence in it: And of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Accident may at any time happen to Impede it, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract it, or Discourage it.</item>
                  <item n="10">10. That to this end Duplicates of the said Council's Journal, Books of Letters and Instructions, be constantly Transcribed, not only for the use of the said Grand Commissioners, but that they may be the better preserved, and remain upon Record.</item>
                  <item n="11">11. That the said Grand Commissioners may have Power, with the Leave of His Majesty, to propound some <hi>Praemium</hi> as an Extraordinary Reward from His Majesty, to encourage the Diligence of the said Directors: Which <hi>Praemium</hi> therefore is to be only out of the clear Gain that shall be made of the said Trade, through the Prudent and Faithful Management and Conduct of the said Directors: And shall be therefore such a part of the said clear Gain only, as to His Majesty's Wisdom shall be thought fit.</item>
                  <item n="12">12. That the said Grand Commissioners have further Power, with the consent of His Majesty, to give Directions in all such cases of Difficulty, as shall at any time arise about the said Fishery. As also to Hear and Determine all such other Debates relating to the said Affair, as the said Directors may be doubtful in, or may not be able to agree amongst them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves fully about.</item>
                  <item n="13">13. That if upon the good Success and Blessing of God upon the said Fishery, any of the Nobility, Gentry, or other Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Persons, shall desire to Incorporate themselves, for the further Assistance and carrying on of the said Design, and for the making the Trade of the said Fishing the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly a Publick and National Concern: Or if the said Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectors shall find it for the Service of His Majesty, and of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:207630:25"/> absolute Necessity for the promoting of the said Fishing, to take into Association any of His Majesty's Subjects of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with reference to the Fishing of either of the said Kingdoms. In either of these cases, such a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod is to be set down by the said Directors for the manner of it, as is to be wholly approved by His Majesty, and the said Grand Commissioners.</item>
                  <item n="14">14. That such a Fund or Stock, that may be both Annual and certain, be by the special Grace and Favour of His Majesty Granted and Assigned, for the Undertaking and carrying on the said Fishing; and not only for the Increase, but for the better Protection and Defence of it, and for the defray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sallaries and Contingences of such as shall be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the immediate Directors of it.</item>
                  <item n="15">15. That for the better preventing either any Impediment or Interruption that may be endeavoured to be given by any, at any time hereafter in or about the said Fishing, It is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Humbly Propounded, That the Application of the said Fund or Stock entirely for the carrying on of the said Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and for the Ends now mentioned, may be setled by Act of Parliament: Together with so many of these Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posals, or of such others as shall be thought fit to be allowed or approved by His Majesty.</item>
                  <item n="16">16. For the greater Encouragement of the said Fishing, and as a particular mark of the Parliament's Approbation of it, and of their desire to promote it: It is further Humbly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, That all such Persons as shall Subscribe a Stock to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Advancement of the said Fishing, and all such others as shall be any ways employed for or in the managing of it, or for pursuing such Instructions and Directions about it, as shall any way be derived from His Majesty's Authority in it, shall be expresly declared to be taken into Protection by the Government, whether they be Natives of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty's Dominions, or whether they be Foreigners: Together with all such Ships, Busses, Boats, and all other Vessels or Craft whatsoever that shall be employed by any of the Persons so associated in the said Fishing; or by any deriving Authority from His Majesty in it. And likewise that all Ships and Vessels which shall be built or bought by the Stock appointed for the said Fishing, or by any that shall further Subscribe to it, or be Associated with it, shall be exempted from Paying
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:207630:26"/> Duty, Custom or Impost, for the Fish which they shall Export. Or for whatsoever Salt, Barrel-Staves, Net-Yarn, Flax or Hemp, for making the said Net-Yarn, which they shall Import for the said Fishing, during such time as to the wisdom of his Majesty and the Parliament shall be thought fit.</item>
                  <item n="17">17. That for the greater Encouragement of Merchants and others of Wisdom, Knowledge, and Experience, to Subscribe towards the carrying on the said Fishery: And for the better making the said Undertaking, <hi>The General Concern of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> it is further humbly Propounded, That all such Losses as shall proceed from the meer Casualty of the Seas by Storms or Shipwracks: And all such Losses as shall happen through any Injury or Violence that shall be offered us by any of the Subjects of the Neighbouring Princes or States about us, shall be so far born and eased, out of the said Publick Stock (which shall be designed towards it) as to the Wisdom of his Majesty and of the Parliament shall be thought fit.</item>
                  <item n="18">18. That for the farther Encouragement of all sorts of Persons, to Subscribe to the said Fishing; and for Encouraging all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of Quality the more, to make the said Undertaking <hi>The General Concern of this Nation,</hi> it is likewise humbly Propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, That as ample Privileges may be given by his Majesty and the Parliament, to all such Persons as shall be Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in the said Fishing Stock, as have been of late Granted by the Act of Parliament in <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the General Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking of the said Fishing in that Kingdom.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="15">15. And in regard, not only the valuableness but the intire pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticableness of all these Proposals, doth wholly depend upon the finding out such a Fund or Stock as is herein mentioned. And up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on clearing the Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zability of carrying on the said Fishing, in a way of more advantage than the <hi>Hollander</hi> is in at present; and forming such Instructions as are propounded: Wherefore, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the compassing both the said Ends, as such a Method or Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is herewith humbly tendred; and such a Body of Instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for pursuing the said Fishing, as may be answerable to the Ends which are now laid down, and to the Advantages here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mentioned: So there are some Gentlemen, who, out of their affection to his Majesties Service, and out of the great Sense they have, how much the gaining of the said Fishing doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and concern this Nation, have digested some Proposals to tender to his Majesty, about the Prae-emption of Salt, with such
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:207630:26"/> a moderate Duty upon it, as may be neither grievous to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor burthensome to the Manufacture of it. By the Benefit of which Prae-emption alone, nevertheless it is hoped, That about Twenty thousand Pounds Sterling <hi>per</hi> year, or more, may be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily Raised, as a Fund or Stock, that may not only give a Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the said Fishing; but by a constant application to it, may by degrees increase it, and in time be able to perfect it: and may, if the Blessing of God give a Success to it, incourage divers others of the Nation to contribute both their Estates and Advice for the farther help of it: So as, it is hoped, nothing will be wanting, that may conduce to the compleating our Desire and Design, of undermining the <hi>Hollander</hi> in the present Possession he hath of the said Fishing; which, as it is the main and principal scope of this Paper, so of the Discourse hereunto annexed.</p>
               <p n="16">16. That both the said Discourses and the said Proposals about the Prae-emption of Salt, have the rather been tender'd at this season, in regard of the present Treaty which his Majesty is in with <hi>Holland:</hi> And that, considering how much his Majesty and his Subjects have suffered from that Nation, it is hoped that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this Conjuncture of Affairs, will prove more grateful to the Parliament, or more obliging to the Nation it self; and therefore, that nothing may be more for his Majesties present Service.</p>
               <p n="17">17. That by how much the more plainly and obviously it doth appear, That the promoting of the Fishery is for the necessary Good and Interest of this Nation; and by how much the more highly grateful and obliging it must needs be, to see such a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation laid, as may in probability every way tend to the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Greatness of it; by so much the more injurious and distast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful it must justly render the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to the generality of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if they shall either wrongfully disturb us in it, or if they shall endeavour by Violence to force us from it.</p>
               <p n="18">18. This Proposal is the rather Presented at this Season, That upon this occasion, the Ancient Rights of his Majesty, and the known Customs of this Kingdom, may be farther examined and enquired into; <hi>viz.</hi> For the granting not only a Guard and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, but express License to all Fishers whatsoever, Fishing in any part of the Seas, from the West of <hi>England</hi> even unto <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> and for the demanding a Duty upon all Fish so caught in any part of the said Seas, towards defraying the charge of the said Guard and Protection; not only from the Subjects belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:207630:27"/> unto <hi>France,</hi> but from the Subjects belonging to the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and the Dukes of <hi>Britany.</hi> And that if the said Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom of giving License and Protection to all Fishers, be found to be the undoubted Right of his Majesty, and of this Kingdom, the said Custom may receive such farther Sanction, Assertion, and Confirmation from his Majesty, and from the Parliament, as to the Wisdom of his Majesty and of the Parliament, shall at this juncture of time be judged most convenient.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Lastly, This Proposal is the rather tendred, because, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the extraordinary Gain which the <hi>Hollander</hi> doth continually reap from our own Seas by the said Fishing; and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the many Laws which he hath made for the Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging, Regulating, and Promoting his own Fishing; [which are about Thirty] And, notwithstanding the several Affronts that have been offered us, both in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and in our own Channel by their Fishers: And, notwithstanding that both his Majesty's Father, and his Majesty's Grandfather, have been constrained by their respective Proclamations, to vindicate their Rights against the Insolencies of the said <hi>Dutch,</hi> both to the said Seas, and to the said Fishing: <hi>Yet, no Parliament of</hi> England hath hitherto, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made any Law purposely or principally for increasing the said Fishing; or hath ever raised or appointed any Stock towards it; or hath erected any Council about it; or hath incouraged the Nation it self to Undertake it; or hath warranted them their Protection in it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In the next place shall be super-added, a few Pages of a Treatise witten by Mr <hi>Andrew Yarranton,</hi> (entituled, <hi>The Second Part of</hi> Englands <hi>Improvement by Sea and Land)</hi> who, upon much Travel and Observation, (amongst other things) thought fit to give his Furtherance and Advice towards the Undertaking and Management of the Fishery. Evincing, how we may outdo our Neighbours therein; [which may serve by way of Answer to their Objection, who would have us believe, that we cannot do it to the like Advantage, and at lower Charge, <hi>&amp;c.]</hi> which is Transcribed in his own words, as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So Prodigiously Rich is the Fishing Trade, and so plainly the Right of the King of <hi>England,</hi> That with good reason is our neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence taken notice of, by all <hi>Europe;</hi> and our Prudence questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by it, that we keep so little a share of it to our selves as we do; and let our Neighbours grow great and haughty by the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:207630:27"/> and full enjoyment of that considerable Trade. 'Twas a most unlucky piece of Goodness, That some of our former Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ever suffered a Foreign Buss to visit the <hi>English</hi> Coasts. The Tributes and Acknowledgments were paid them then, in return of that Favour. And most unlucky still it was, that the sad Calamitous Times, in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. prevented his Resolution, <hi>of Correcting the Dutch, and keeping the Wealth of the Seas to his own People:</hi> And that the Civil Wars, some time after, gave-occasion to the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to fix themselves in that Trade; and 'tis now a difficult matter (by force) to dispossess them of it.</p>
               <p>This only Trade hath been the occasion of their present Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. This hath given them their mighty numbers of Seamen, their vast Fleets of Ships, and a Foundation of all their other Trades. But they could not so easily have Ingrossed the Fishery to themselves (notwithstanding those opportunities they have had of advancing themselves, whilst we have not had Leisure to look abroad) if at other times we had used a due Prudence to withdraw it from them.</p>
               <p>We have endeavoured with Force, and a prodigious expence of Treasure and Blood, to bring down their Hearts, and level their Trades: And had they dared to meet us in open Sea, no doubt we had done their Business, and our own: But they are too Wise to do so, without all the advantage in the World; and therefore have commonly so managed themselves, by standing on the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive part, by prolonging a War; by retiring within their Sands, and natural defences of their Seas, that we have been hardly able at any time, to do any thing considerable upon them; never to vindicate the Fishery to our selves; nor indeed, to bring them to their acknowledgment for that Privilege.</p>
               <p>We have endeavour'd otherwise also to raise our Fishery and depress theirs; as, By raising Joint Stocks for the buying Busses and Nets, and all other Necessaries for so great an Affair; and by making Companies, and gathering large Sums of Money to be employed in the same manner. But all these industrious attempts have had ill Success, and have ended in nought but a visible loss to the Undertakers, and reproach to the Nation.</p>
               <p>How there should be these miscarriages, it may seem wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to most Men; when the Fish are on our own Coasts, when we have had good Harbours, and the whole Nation praying for the Prosperity of the Undertaking: And if you read all the Books that have been wrote on this Subject of the Fishery, you shall not find one give the reason of our Failures.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:207630:28"/>
               <p> You shall find them plentiful in setting forth the great Riches attending thereon; the mighty increase of Seamen; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant imploy of the Poor, and the inlargement of their several Trades: Not one word of the grounds of our ill success, or of the reasons of the Prosperity of the <hi>Dutch;</hi> or of the remedies to be made use of by us, to recover our Loss and Credit. Alas! Without these last enquiries, what signify the first? but to raise our Grief and Torment, when we know the advantages of the Fishery, but cannot attain to them. Methinks, If they had not been very Ingenious and Prudent Men, which had passed by these Enquiries, I could presently be satisfied, that I could give a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution to them; Nor do I despair that I can, nevertheless. For, the things are so evident to my self, that I cannot doubt, but they will be so to all others also.</p>
               <p>What then is the reason, Why our <hi>English</hi> Fishery is Unprospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and the <hi>Dutch</hi> Successful?</p>
               <p>'Tis in short, That we Fish intolerably Dear, and they exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cheap.</p>
               <p>What also, if this inconveniency of ours might be removed, by being taught to Fish cheaper than the <hi>Dutch</hi> possibly can? For it is not to be doubted, but as cheapness is one of the most essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial parts of Trade: And as he that can sell a Commodity cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, shall certainly have the Trade of that Commodity; so, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fish cheaper than we now, and therefore can sell cheaper; they therefore consequently, have the Trade of the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shery; and by the same reason, when we are able to Fish cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than they, we shall carry away the Fishing Trade from them also. For, The Trade must necessarily be there, where 'tis car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on cheapest. No other Reason can there possibly be, why the <hi>Dutch</hi> should get the Fishery to themselves.</p>
               <p>If you say, The regularity of their Trade, or their Industry may effect this, and deny that they Fish cheaper; you may easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be answered, as to the two first parts of your Assertion; for they are both resolved into cheapness. Industry promotes cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and so does Regularity; both of them are but Promoters of that which I have told you is the supporter of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Trade: And as to the latter part of the Assertion, you must be convinced by Fact.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:207630:28"/>
               <p> I will therefore shew you, <hi>First,</hi> How the <hi>Dutch</hi> manage their Fishe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the best advantage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> In what chargeable ways the <hi>English</hi> proceed in the Fishery.</p>
               <p>And then, at last, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I will endeavour to shew you, how the defects of our <hi>English</hi> Fishery may be removed, and it be made chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per than it is with the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>As to the Management of the Fishery to the best Advantage by the</hi> Hollanders.</head>
                  <p>The great Trade of building Busses, making Nets, and doing all other things which are convenient for the Fishing Trade, is at <hi>Enecusen,</hi> upon the South-Sea, and at several places adjoyning: So that, all the conveniencies for that Trade lying near together, it is carried on with the greater Expeditness and Cheapness. 'Tis not in the power of any Man to run the prices of things high, where there is a mighty number of the same Profession about him, who all of them work with the greatest Diligence that can be, that they may not be undersold by another.</p>
                  <p>In other places (where Two or Three only of the same Trade reside) they very often presume upon a necessity of the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Countries dealing with them; and therefore live profusely, and demand intolerable prices for their Commodities; which (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their way of living) they cannot afford cheaper. Here is no ground for such an Extravagancy. You must live moderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and sell cheap, or you cannot drive a Trade in these Parts.</p>
                  <p>What promotes, especially the Building their Busses as cheap as they do, but their good Husbandry? In always being provided with Timber, fitted to all Dimensions? So that, they can no sooner resolve on Building a Buss, but the Timber is instantly laid out for its Foundation and Bones, and with mighty Expedition the Buss is raised.</p>
                  <p>And, now the Buss is raised, what can they do less than take care to preserve it from all Storms and Bruises whilest it lies at home in Harbour? And therefore they have cut Rivers and Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels for its quiet Repose; which requires not the Charge either of Cable or Anchor, or of any Person to look to it, when not employed in Fishing. These are great Advantages. But see what mighty ones follow. The Busses and Nets, and the Tackling belonging thereunto, are always to the Owners sufficient Credit to take up Ready Moneys, either to be employed in the Voyage,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:207630:29"/> or to buy Salt or Victuals, or for any other necessary Occasions: And the Title to the Buss never so much as Questionable, she be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing always under a Register: A thing of no small Importance to all Persons therein concerned, were it well considered. For, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all Men whatsoever are made capable with swiftness to run their Money into the Fishing Trade, and buying a part of, or the whole Buss. And since there is such Security, what, should the Money lye rusting in the Bags? No, it is not so; it tumbles out into Trade immediately: The Owner either willingly running the hazard himself, or Letting it at Three in the Hundred, Interest; nay, sometimes for Two, hath the Fisherman enough to serve his Occasions: An unspeakable Benefit is this to him, and a Prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Advancement to the Trade in general.</p>
                  <p>But oh! This Trade is so sweet (see the Care and Diligence of the States about it) no less than Forty Placaets made by them for the Curing and well Ordering of the Herrings, as the Season of the Year shall require. What quick dispatches have the Fishery in all its Affairs, when ever it comes before the Body of the States? They give them all sufficient Guards, whilest they are Laboriously drawing up into their Ships the Riches of the Sea; and permit the Fishers to end all their Differences by Men of their own Trade, that it may be concluded with quickness and small charge. So great are all these Advantages of the Fishery, that one would think, that one need not have another; and yet they have a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable one: They make Salt upon Salt with <hi>Portugal</hi> Salt and Sea-water mixt together; and by this means they have this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity cheap, which is used so considerably in the Fishery; And under these beneficial Circumstances is the Fishery of <hi>Holland</hi> (at all times) managed.</p>
                  <p>I do not here intend to speak of their Benefits and Returns in the Fishing Trade, by the vast Exchange and Barter which they make with their Fish for other Commodities, in most parts of the World. 'Tis enough for my purpose, that I have given you the several conveniencies that do attend them, until their Fish (caught and cured) be brought into their Harbours.</p>
                  <p>But now, Let us see how blessedly the <hi>English</hi> Fishery is mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. We are likely indeed, to keep pace with the <hi>Dutch</hi> in that Trade, when it is carried on so, as if we had studied to make it as chargeable as it could be.</p>
                  <p>The building of Busses is hardly known by us; Or, where it is known, it is a mighty charge above what the <hi>Dutch</hi> Build at.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:207630:29"/> Such bad Husbands are we in providing Stores of Timber, and sorting it out for all the Dimensions of our Buss: Besides, our Timber costs us more, (though we have it off our own Soyle) than it doth the <hi>Hollander,</hi> that fetches every Plank of it from <hi>Germany,</hi> or other remote Places.</p>
                  <p>Our Nets, and all our Tackle convenient for the Fishery, are not here to be had, but at much greater Rates than what the <hi>Dutch</hi> pay for them: And if they chance to want mending at any time, it is impossible as matters go with us now, we cannot with speed enough have them done here, but must be forced to send them over to <hi>Enecusen</hi> in <hi>Holland</hi> to have them mended, with greater Expedition and Cheapness.</p>
                  <p>And now, perhaps, the Fishing time is over, and the Buss is brought into Harbour, (not into Cuts or Channels for that purpose) but she must have Anchor and Cable to keep her to her Station: She continually suffers the unkindness of frequent Tides. And here only is the care of our Busses eminent, that we provide Men to look to them, and are even expensive rather than suffer them to lye alone. So great is our Negligence, and so small is our Policie.</p>
                  <p>But we even outdo our selves in the concern of Salt: Our Folly even in this alone, is sufficient to ruine the Fishing design; for we have no Salt Works wholly applicable to, and at the command of our Fishery; and therefore we expose it to all the uncertainties in the World. Let but a War fall out between us and some Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Prince or State, and presently Salt rises to such excessive Rates, that the Fishery cannot be carried on, while it continues so. Trade cannot endure such a mighty inconvenience, and is impatient of staying any where, but where it may be even and clever.</p>
                  <p>Well, The Fisherman has need of a little Money to mend or buy some Nets, or some Provisions for his Voyage; let us see af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what fashion he will be furnished. The Property of his Buss is not so certain, as to take up Money upon it; nor draw in a Partner. If the poor Man would any ways procure a Supply, he must bring his Sureties, and pay at least Six in the Hundred; and let him be sure to observe the very minute of Payment, or he will be swinged unconscionably by his Creditor. But perhaps, he cannot get Security, and then his Voyage is hindred; and no body has the benefit of his disappointment but the <hi>Dutch,</hi> And his Wife, who, by this means, has his Company the longer. I need
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:207630:30"/> not declare any other disadvantages of the <hi>English</hi> Fishery, as, A long Process of Law upon Controversies. Few or no Directions for its management, from publick Authority, And, Persons employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein, many times very unfitting for that Business.</p>
                  <p>What I have already shewn, is enough to convince any Man, that we manage our Fishery basely, and at a vast Expence, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and that we are deficient of the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that they enjoy.</p>
                  <p>I should now proceed, to The redress of these mischiefs; but I must first vent my sorrow, and lament a while, that we have thus long lain under these inconveniencies, to the utter suppressing this Trade, which would have given the Nation a mighty Strength and Treasure; which would have employed thousands of poor People, who heretofore, and now, want Bread to maintain them for want of Work: And to the raising some of our Neighbours (as well <hi>Hansmen</hi> as <hi>Dutch,</hi> though I have not named them) to great Riches; To a Power and Impudence of Confronting our selves, and maintaining their Insolence by that very Strength, which our remisness and negligence has given them.</p>
                  <p>I come at last to shew how these miscarriages may be retrieved; how we may gain the Fishery to our selves, and exclude the <hi>Dutch</hi> who have enjoyed it so long already. And certainly this can never be done, but by putting our selves in a way to sell the Commodity cheaper than they. I would have said also, we ought to sell our Fish as well conditioned as they; but that it's plain, Goodness is included in Cheapness. For I may sell a Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity not cheaper than another, though I sell it at a lower price, if the Commodity be not comparable to his in Goodness.</p>
                  <p>This thing, <hi>Cheapness,</hi> is, as before I have said, the great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troller of all Trade; and is (as it were) the waiting Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to Trade, who must be obtained before ever 'tis possible to gain the Mistress. This is so clear, that I need not recount the common instances of its effects over all the World. By this means Empories have been shuffled from one place to another: And it hath been the common Artifice of such as have desired to Engross the Trade of their Neighbours, to act by such Methods.</p>
                  <p>I will go on therefore, and endeavour to inform you, how this Cheapness may be introduced; And, in order to it will use this Method.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>First,</hi> To shew you, how and where sufficient Iron and Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:207630:30"/> may be had to build Busses, and how it may be contrived, that we may build them cheaper than the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> To recommend a place to you, where we may have Cuts and Channels, and all other Conveniencies for the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in of Busses, as well as they in <hi>Holland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Propose where a convenient Sea-City may be built for those that are employed in the Fishery, to inhabit in; and how it may be conveniently Erected.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To shew you, That we have so great a conveniency for the making of Salt, that we may at all times afford it much cheaper than the <hi>Dutch</hi> can; and that this Salt will be much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for Curing Fish, than any that is now Extant. And,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Offer some reasons, for the allowing certain Privileges to the Sea-City, and the Inhabitants thereof, for their Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and Trading cheap.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>As to the first Proposal of making Busses Cheap.</head>
                  <p>In many places of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Timber lies wasting and decaying for want of Money to make the ways passable to some Rivers; and the making such Rivers Navigable, for the bringing down Timber for its Exportation: So that, at present, the Timber is of little or no advantage to the Owners or the Publick: And this is so, more especially in the County of <hi>Wexford</hi> near the River <hi>Slane.</hi> There is a Wood with prodigious quantities of Timber, which may be brought to a convenient place upon the said River, for Eight Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings the Tun or Load; There, all the Timber and Beams of the Buss may be fixed; and then she may be taken off the Stocks; and the River (with Four or Five thousand Pounds charge) may be made sufficiently useful for that purpose. Then she may be conveyed towards the Sea by several Flashes, from place to place, till you come to <hi>Eniscorthy</hi> or <hi>Scarawalsh,</hi> where she may be fitted up and finished. In like manner may all sorts of Timber be conveyed down the <hi>Slane,</hi> for Exportation.</p>
                  <p>As to what Iron is necessary towards the building of Busses, it may be made upon this River, with the vast Timber that now lies Rotting; and the Offal of such Timber as shall be used in the building of Busses: and of the Forest of Dean Cindars, and Iron Stone; which Metal makes the best Iron in the World; except what is made of Iron Stone, dug out of the Clay-Hill near <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> in <hi>Shropshire.</hi> And the price of this Iron so made, will not
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:207630:31"/> be above Nine Pounds the Tun, in the Bar, and Eleven Pounds drawn out into Bolts, as it is in <hi>Germany,</hi> for the use of the <hi>Dutch</hi> in building their Shipping.</p>
                  <p>For your better Satisfaction, take here the rates of making one Tun of Iron, Fifteen Miles upon the <hi>Slane.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>l.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>s.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>d.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Of Iron, Stone and Cindars, carried out of the Forest of <hi>Dean,</hi> by Sea to <hi>Wexford,</hi> and so unto the place where it is to be converted to Iron; Two Tuns of Cindars, and One Tun of Iron Stone (which Three Tun of Mine will make One Tun of Iron) delivered in <hi>Weymouth,</hi> will cost.</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>18</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>The Carriage of Three Tun of Iron Stone, and Cindars from <hi>Weymouth</hi> to <hi>Waxford.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>The Carriage of Three Tun from <hi>Wexford</hi> to the place intended for the Fornace.</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>12</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Two Loads and half of Charcoal, to make One Tun of Sow-Iron, at 8 <hi>s. per</hi> Load.</cell>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Founders Wages for making One Tun of Sow-Iron.</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>So the Tun of Sow-Iron made in the place, will be</cell>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                           <cell>14</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Two thousand seven hundred of Sow-Iron will make One Tun of Bar-Iron, whereof the charges of making One Tun of Bar-Iron, will be</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>For making One Tun of Bar-Iron to the Finery, or Hammer-man</cell>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Three Load of Charcoal to make One Tun of Bar-Iron, at 8 <hi>s. per</hi> Load,</cell>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>All which makes the Tun of Bar-Iron delivered in the place,</cell>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                           <cell>12</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>For Drawing One Tun of Iron into Bolts the <hi>German</hi> way,</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>So the charge of Iron drawn into Bars is 8 <hi>l.</hi> 12 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> and in Bolts 2 <hi>l.</hi> in all,</cell>
                           <cell>10</cell>
                           <cell>12</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that which will contribute much to the cheapness of working Iron into divers and various Commodities, is, That with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:207630:31"/> Twelve Miles of the place, fit and convenient for this design of building Busses, there is the best and durablest Pit-coals fit for Smiths, that ever yet I saw, 'tis called <hi>Kill-Kenny-Coals.</hi> Here are therefore redundant Advantages, besides the promotion of the cheapness of building Busses, that the Trade of working Iron in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Commodities may be highly advanced; So that, in that also we may out do, and under sell our Neighbours.</p>
                  <p>But to come narrowly to the consideration of what I have said in Relation to Busses, Timber is by that means, to be had at the third Penny, the <hi>Dutch</hi> now pay for theirs; which they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to fetch out of <hi>Germany;</hi> and Iron at Two thirds the <hi>Dutch</hi> now pay for theirs.</p>
                  <p>When the Buss is Building we shall have Advantages also: For, Provisions may be had for the Workmen at Two thirds of what it costs the <hi>Dutch:</hi> And certainly, all this considered together, there will be no small assistance found out, for procuring cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in our Fishery, and under-selling the <hi>Hollanders.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet, To set out and compleat the Buss, there are still wanting Pitch, Tar and Masts, which may be brought with as little charge to the place proposed, for Erecting Busses, betwixt <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> as it is now to <hi>Holland.</hi> Rope and Canvas (if we please) may be also procured, as cheap as by them.</p>
                  <p>And now the Buss is fitted out, let her be laded with all sorts of Timber, ready prepared for Shipping, as also with Iron Bolts, Trindle-pins, and Planks, to be carried to the New Sea-City, hereafter mentioned, to be used either for Building or Repairing other Fishing Busses; or for occasions in Shipping or Building.</p>
                  <p>I am ready to justify the cheap Building of Busses, I have here proposed, to any Man whatsoever, that denies it. Nor am I stint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up only to the Woods upon the River <hi>Slane;</hi> for there are se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Woods in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that lies very conveniently, and may be almost as useful as those. So that, upon the whole, I dare aver, That <hi>Ireland</hi> may be made as beneficial, or more to <hi>England,</hi> than <hi>Norway</hi> is to the <hi>Dane;</hi> if matters were but fitly applied, and the cheapness it would give us in Trade, taken hold of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For places to be made to hold the Busses when not employed abroad, and thereby to save all that needless Expence we are at present at, to preserve the Busses from the damage they commonly receive, when they lye in our great Rivers; and thereby to make our Husbandry as great as 'tis with the</hi> Dutch.</p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:207630:32"/>
                  <p> Certainly there cannot be a greater conveniency than is in the Isle of <hi>Doggs,</hi> or <hi>Blackwall Levell;</hi> An Isle seated in the <hi>Thames,</hi> (one of the best Rivers in the World) just over against <hi>Greenwich.</hi> This Level lyes so low within its Banks, that the <hi>Thames</hi> at High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, rises Five or Six Foot above its surface: By which means, the Channels may, with very little charge, be Cut; the Earth not being to be carried away, but thrown up to raise a Bank, for making the Channels sufficient to keep in the Tide. If the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels be cut Six Foot deep, the Water will be Eleven Foot deep in them; so that any Buss fully laded, there will be Water suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for to Swim in and out.</p>
                  <p>And upon the Banks of these Cuts may be Built the Sea-City, before proposed for the conveniency of Fishermen, and others concerned in the Fishery; and then the Buss may be laid up just under (or before) the Fisherman's house; and the Water (by Locks) may be kept back at the Re-flowing of the Tyde, for the more convenient and quiet living of the Buss: Here will be no need of Ancor or Cable, or Man to look after the Buss.</p>
                  <p>Here also may be made all manner of Ropes and Nets for the use of the Fishery; and here may be made Docks convenient to Build Ships and Busses, and Yards to receive in all things that may be wanting, for the Equipping of the Buss.</p>
                  <p>And that the Building such a City is necessary for the carrying on so great a Design, we may consider, how easily a new Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking is destroyed in the beginning, without all the Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Helps in the World, that may be afforded.</p>
                  <p>This hath been apparent in the setting up all Manufactures whatsoever; and from whence it has been a common Policy to settle a Staple in some certain Town, where 'tis best to be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, by the Members of the Trade living together. And this Cohabitation has been a frequent cause of Industry and great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements: one Man advancing the Husbandry and Invention of another: It has prevented Cheats, and Coznages, and Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Prices. For every Man is cautious that he deals honestly, and sells at a moderate Price, when he knows he shall be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise supplanted in his Trade, by his more honest Neighbour. But how much does it concern us to provide these Conveniencies, for the Advancement of the Fishery? when we shall not be able to make any thing of it, unless we are able to under-sell the <hi>Dutch,</hi> (a vigilant and industrious People, already fixed in that Trade) who know their Support and Being depends upon it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:207630:32"/> will by all means whatsoever, endeavour to ruine the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Next comes the Consideration of Salt.</head>
                  <p>It has been for many years disputable in <hi>Holland,</hi> what Salt is best for curing the Herrings; and what sorts of Salt are fittest to be used in the several Fishing Seasons. And there hath been much Labour and practical Experience used, to bring the Salt to such Perfections as 'tis now with them. But, Notwithstanding all their Practice and Enquiry, there are many good Arguments to be produced, which may prove, that great part of the Salt now used in curing their Fish, is not so good as the World takes it to be.</p>
                  <p>I am not at present for Controversies, but I dare affirm, and shall be ready at any time to make it appear, That there is in <hi>England</hi> Salt-Brine running at wast, of such noble and good qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that if it were made and converted into good sizeable Salt, fit for salting Herrings, it would surpass any Salt that is now Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; and make the Herrings that are salted therewith, bring at all Markets more Money by the Barrel, than twice the value of such Salt, as will be used in Salting such Herrings shall come to.</p>
                  <p>This is a rare Salt indeed; and removes not only those mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, which at present (in the Fishery) have relation to Salt, but seems, in a mighty measure, to promise us the Fishing Trade.</p>
                  <p>Salt was a charge before to us, but now, 'twill be the occasion of a greater Gain; affording us upon the return by the Sale of the Fish, double its charge and worth: And 'twill be much better for us to use Salt thus, than if Fish could be cured without Salt, and sold at the Price 'tis now at. Whilst this Advantage is enjoyed by us, still must the <hi>Dutch</hi> be at the same Expence for their Salt: They must first fetch their Salt from <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Portugal;</hi> and if they make Salt upon Salt, they must fetch their Brine from Sea to mix with <hi>Portugal</hi> Salt: This is Toylsome and Chargeable; but ours will come at much lower Rates. It may be delivered in <hi>Cornwal</hi> for Salting the Pilchards; and at the Dogger-Sands for Salting Herrings, even at Twelve Pence the Bushel. For, The Salt-Brine lies so conveniently, That it may be conveyed in Pipes to a place plentiful of Coals, and joining to a great Navigable Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, by which a Ship of Fifty Tuns may come to it.</p>
                  <p>A Sample of this Salt shall be at Mr. <hi>Man</hi>'s Coffee-house, at <hi>Charing-cross;</hi> at <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s Coffee-house in <hi>Exchange-Alley,</hi> and at
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:207630:33"/>
                     <hi>Richard</hi>'s at <hi>Temple-bar;</hi> where some Persons of Honour will at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test the truth of the Discovery, and of the quantity that may at all times be had. And how can we now fear (if what I have said be true) but that the Fishery must certainly be ours? We shall have cheaper Timber, cheaper Iron by far, than the <hi>Dutch;</hi> other things necessary for a Buss, as cheap as they. Salt incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perably better, as convenient Channels and better, being seated in the middle of a well ordered Town. But,</p>
                  <p>To these mighty advantages, how happy should we be, if one more were given us? <hi>viz,</hi> To have great Privileges and Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities conferr'd upon the Sea-faring City. As much may be said for this, and more than what was urged before, for a Cities being granted. How can there be too great immunities given, for the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tling so great a Design as the Fishery? Great Privileges will draw in Numbers of Inhabitants, from at home and abroad; does also cause Cheapness, (the essential part of Trade:) and indeed is as convenient for Raising the Fishing Enterprize, as any thing that can be named.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>I therefore lastly Humbly offer these Privileges may be granted the Fishing City.</head>
                     <item n="1">1. A Freedom from Taxes, for a certain number of Years.</item>
                     <item n="2">2. Freedom from Customs, for all Goods that shall be used about the Fishing Trade, and in making Busses, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="3">3. That the Houses in the City, and Busses, may be put under a Register, and so become Transferrable Credit.</item>
                     <item n="4">4. That Granaries and Lumber-houses to take in Corn, and Pawns by way of Registry may be allowed.</item>
                     <item n="5">5. That Naturalization may be allowed to all Strangers and Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, and Liberty of Conscience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item n="6">6. That a Fund be fixed, for Maintenance of all such as shall fall into Want, who are employed in the Fishing Trade; and did not break by their own Knavery or Negligence.</item>
                     <item n="7">7. That all Differences betwixt Party and Party, relating to the Fishing Trade, may be ended by Members of the said City and Trade.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>These Privileges proposed for the Fishing City, and what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I offered for the Redress of the ill managements in our Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shery, will, no doubt, answer the intended End. Nothing being amiss in our Fishery, but a way is shewn how it may be Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:207630:33"/> Nothing good and commendable in the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fishery; but a Discovery is made, how we may outdo and under-sell them.</p>
                  <p>As I have ventured on the Grounds and Reasons of the Fishing Trade, I doubt not, but (if the Parliament approve of my Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon it) they will be willing to raise a small Sum for the advancement of this vast Design of the Fishery. But 'tis strange, That a certain Gentleman should advise the Parliament (in Print) to raise Six hundred thousand Pounds for this Enterprize, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving any Reasons, how the Obstructions that may make so noble a Design ineffectual in the end, might be removed.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. To draw towards a Conclusion of this Collection, take an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stract of the Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> respecting the Fishery Trade, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements thereto: Taken out of the last Impression of the Collection of Acts, of Tunnage and Poundage, and Book of Rates, Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1689. (and other Statutes) which being in most or many Merchants hands, they may examine the same, and find the Contents of them more at large in the several Pages of the said Book herein after mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>Pag.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>44.</cell>
                           <cell>Under the Head of Fish, it is noted, That all sorts of Fish, <hi>English</hi> taken, and brought in <hi>English</hi> Ships, ought to pay no Custom, as by the Statute of 5 <hi>Eliz. Regin. Cap.</hi> 5.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>115.</cell>
                           <cell>By the Act of 12 <hi>Car.</hi> II. <hi>Regis,</hi> entituled, <hi>An Act for Encouraging and Increasing of Shipping and Navigation:</hi> That Fish, Fins and Oyl, not made and cured by <hi>English</hi> men, shall pay double Strangers Customs, upon their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>121.</cell>
                           <cell>By the same Act it is provided, This Act shall not extend to lay Aliens Duties on Salt made in <hi>Scotland;</hi> nor to any Fish caught, saved and cured by the People of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and Imported directly in <hi>Scotch</hi> built Ships, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>139.</cell>
                           <cell>In the Act of 12 <hi>Car.</hi> II. entituled, <hi>A Subsidy granted to the King, of Tunnage and Poundage, &amp;c.</hi> It is provided, That all manner of Fish <hi>English</hi> taken, and brought by <hi>English</hi> bottoms into this Realm; and all manner of Fresh Fish and Bestial, that shall come into this Realm, are except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and foreprized.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>141.</cell>
                           <cell>In the same Act it is provided, That it shall and may be lawful, to all and every his Majesties Subjects, at his and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:207630:34"/> their will and pleasure, To Convey and Transport out of this Realm in Ships and other Vessels, of any the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of this Realm, all and any kind of Herrings, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sea-Fish, to be taken in the Sea, by any the Subjects aforesaid, from or out of any Port or Harbour of this Realm, to any place out of your Majesty's Dominions, without paying any Custom, Subsidy, or Poundage Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for the same Herring, or other Fish so Carried and Transported: any thing herein before contained to the contrary notwithstanding.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>In an Act past <hi>Anno</hi> 13 <hi>&amp;</hi> 14 <hi>Car.</hi> II. <hi>Regis Cap.</hi> 24. entituled, <hi>An Act Declaratory concerning Bankrupts;</hi> It is Enacted, That no Person or Persons whatsoever, who have adventured or put in, or who hereafter shall adventure or put in any Sum or Sums of Money, in the <hi>East-India</hi> Company, or <hi>Guiney</hi> Company; or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any Joynt Stock or Stocks of Money, by them or either of them made or raised, or to be made and raised, for and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the maintaining and carrying on the Trade by the said <hi>East-India</hi> Company, or <hi>Guiney</hi> Company, managed or to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged, or who have formerly, or shall hereafter adventure or put in any Sum or Sums of Money, into any Stock or Stocks of Money, for the maintaining and carrying on of the Fishing Trade, or the Trade now called <hi>Royal Fishing Trade;</hi> and shall receive and take his or their Part or Dividend of Fish, Goods, or Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes in Specie, and shall Sell or Exchange the same; shall for or by reason only of such adventure of Monies so put into the said <hi>East-India</hi> Company, or <hi>Guiney</hi> Company, or into any Stock or Stocks, for and towards the said Fishing Trade; or for, or by reason only of the receiving and taking such Fish, Goods, and Merchandizes in Specie, or Selling for Money, or Exchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the same again, be adjudged, taken, esteemed, or reputed a Merchant or Trader, within any Statute or Statutes for Bankrupts, or be liable to the sane, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>Pag.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>165.</cell>
                           <cell>In the Act of 14 <hi>Car.</hi> II. <hi>Regis,</hi> entituled, <hi>An Act for preventing Frauds, &amp;c.</hi> The King by his Commission may appoint Lawful Keys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the Shipping and Lading of Goods; and that no Goods shall be Laden or Dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, but at such lawful Places: Fish taken by his Majesty's Subjects, Bestials, and Salt only excepted.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:207630:34"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>169.</cell>
                           <cell>In the same Act, Pitch, Tar, Salt, Rozen, <hi>Deal</hi> Boards, Fir, Timber, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from the Netherlands or <hi>Germany,</hi> are Prohibited to be Imported in any sort of Ships whatsoever, on Penalty of the Loss of the said Goods and Ships, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>175.</cell>
                           <cell>In the same Act it is provided, That it shall and may be Lawful to Export from any his Majesty's Dominions Fish, into any parts of the Mediterranean Sea, in any <hi>English</hi> Ship or Vessel whatsoever. Provided, That one Moyety of her full Lading, be Fish only. And, In such case to Import any Wares or Merchandizes in the same Ship for that Voyage, without paying any other Rates or Duties of Tunnage or Poundage for the same, than were hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore accustomed. And,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>176.</cell>
                           <cell>That all Salt Imported from <hi>Scotland,</hi> shall pay one half Penny, for every Gallon <hi>Winchester</hi> Measure, at the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereof, to his Majesty.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>194.</cell>
                           <cell>In the Act of 15 <hi>Car.</hi> II. <hi>Regis,</hi> entituled, <hi>An Act for Encouragement of Trade:</hi> It is provided, That it shall and may be Lawful to Ship and Lade, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Salt, for the Fishe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>New-England</hi> and <hi>Newfoundland, &amp;c.</hi> and the same to Transport into any the Lands and Places therein na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; any thing in the foregoing clause to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>199.</cell>
                           <cell>In the same Act, for the encouragement of Herring Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheries, is this Clause, <hi>viz.</hi> And for the Encouragement of the Herring and North Sea, <hi>Isleland,</hi> and <hi>Westmony</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheries, Be it Enacted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That from and after the First day of <hi>August,</hi> 1664. no fresh Herring, fresh Cod, or Haddock, Coalfish, or Gullfish, shall be Imported into <hi>England, Wales, &amp;c.</hi> but in <hi>English</hi> built Ships or Vessels, or in Ships or Vessels <hi>bonâ side,</hi> belonging to <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> and having Certificates thereof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and which hath been Fished, Caught, and Taken in such Ships or Vessels, and not being bought or had of any Strangers born, or out of any Strangers Bottoms, under Pain of Forfeiture of Goods and Vessels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>209.</cell>
                           <cell>In the Act of 18 <hi>Car.</hi> II. <hi>Regis,</hi> entituled, <hi>An Act against Importing Cattle from</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For the better Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of the Fishery of this Kingdom, It is Enacted,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:207630:35"/> That if any Ling, Herring, Cod, or Pilchard, Fresh or Salted, Dryed or Bloated, or any Salmon, Eals or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers taken by any Foreigners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> shall be Imported, Uttered, Sold, or Exposed to Sale in this Kingdom, the same shall be Seized, Sold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>245.</cell>
                           <cell>In the Act of 25 <hi>Car.</hi> II. <hi>Regis,</hi> entituled, <hi>An Act for the Encouragement of the</hi> Green-land <hi>and</hi> East-land <hi>Trade, and for the better securing the Plantation Trade:</hi> Liberty is given for all Persons to Trade thither, and to Import into this Kingdom, all sorts of Oyl, Blubber and Fins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to use and exercise all other Trade, to and from those Parts; without paying any Custom or Duty, for any such Goods brought in by any <hi>English,</hi> or <hi>Welch</hi> Vessels. But if by any Shipping of the King's Colonies and Plantations, then to pay the several Rates mentioned in this Act, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the <hi>English,</hi> who are to have the benefit of this Act, must proceed from <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Green-land.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Pa.</hi> 249.</cell>
                           <cell>In the same last forementioned Act, it is also Enacted, for the Encouragement of the <hi>East-land</hi> Trade, That all Persons shall have free Liberty to Trade into, and from <hi>Sweden, Denmark,</hi> and <hi>Norway, &amp;c.</hi> any thing in the Charter of the Governour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or any other Charter, Grant, Act, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the contrary notwithstanding; and that any Persons of this Realm, that shall desire it, may be admitted into the said Fellowship of Merchants of <hi>East-land</hi> paying for his Admission Forty Shillings, and no more.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>255.</cell>
                           <cell>In the Act past <hi>Anno Primo Regni Jac.</hi> II. entituled, <hi>An Act for the settling the Revenue on his Majesty for Life,</hi> was settled on his said late Majesty for his Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Also, In the Act past <hi>Anno</hi> 5 and 6 of <hi>W. M.</hi> (whereby it is Enacted, That from and after the 25th day of <hi>March,</hi> 1694. There shall be paid to their Majesties, until the 17th day of <hi>May,</hi> 1697. and no longer, for Salt, the Rates and Duties therein mentioned) It is provided, That for all such Fish, therein after mentioned, as shall be Exported from any Port or Place, in <hi>England, Wales,</hi> and <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> into any Parts beyond the Seas, shall be re-paid to the Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, these Rates following, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>l.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>s.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>d.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>For every Vessel of Pilchards, containing 50 Gallons,</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>12</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>For every Barrel of White Herrings,</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>For every Barrel of Red Herrings,</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:207630:35"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>For every Barrel of Salmon,</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>For every Hundred of Cod-fish, Ling, Conger or Hake,</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>15</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>And so proportionably for agreater or smaller Number or Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity; which shall be paid by the Officer appointed to Collect the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties upon Salt, payable by the said Act: And, If the Officer have not Money in hands to pay the same; then, upon his Certificate, the principal Commissioners of Excise shall pay it. And if the Officer refuse to pay or give such Certificate, he shall forfeit dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Sum. [As by the said Act, Relation being thereunto had, for the better certainty thereof, it doth and may more fully and at large Appear.]</p>
                  <p>To all which Premises, for the further encouragement of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to become Subscribers and Ingagers in this Fishery Affair, 'tis thought meet to conclude with the Abstract of a Paper (come to the Collectors hands) which contains the Substance of the things before written; under the Title of <hi>Some Preliminary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations and Advertisements,</hi> &amp;c. Viz.</p>
                  <p>The Advantages thereof may have Demonstration and Evidence, by the great Power and Wealth which our Neighbours have arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unto thereby, In multitudes of Ships and Seamen imployed therein; and Publick Revenues, and Private Advantages of their Merchants, by and with the Commodities and Monies returned, for the Fish they take. Whereas, we have not One Ship of War built or maintained thereby; Nor Mariners bred up (or very few comparitively of equal Skill, Hardiness or Strength, for Labour or Service) Nor Trade by Fish considerable; But buy and are sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied by our Neighbours, at so dear Rates, as none but Persons of great Estates can Eat Fish, with us. And moreover, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume and Spend our Coyn abroad, for the necessaries relating to our Manufactures; which, by the setting up this Trade, would be prevented and increased. And also, Our Towns on the Sea-Coasts, (destroyed or neglected, through the decay of the Fishe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Manufactures) might become Re-edified and Peopled. Our Publick Revenues would become Augmented, to a sufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of preserving the Dominion of these Seas. Our Trade would be vastly spread, even to many unknown, or, at least, untraded Parts. Our poor and idle People would be maintained; and their Earnings in the Manufactures, relating to the Fishery, would ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them, both to buy Cloaths and Victuals; and save the vast Collections made every Year, for their Maintenance in Idleness
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:207630:36"/> and Sloth. In short, We might hereby become the Mart of all Trade, and furnished at all times with Magazines and Stores of all sorts, both for War and Peace, for our selves and all our Neighbours; being better situated for Markets, than any other Trading Nation whatsoever: Which would multiply our Silver and Gold, and reduce it to its Par, as in our most Halcyon days.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quest.</hi> If it be enquired, How shall this Affair be disposed, so as to prevent former Miscarriages and Discouragements?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Answ.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item n="1">1. By a large Stock for carrying on the same, to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most extent it will bear.</item>
                        <item n="2">2. By making a present entrance upon this Trade, by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, under the Constitution, Laws and Rules framed and fixed for that purpose.</item>
                        <item n="3">3. By his Majesty's and the Parliaments further Grants of Aid, Countenance and Protection.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> If it be alledged, 'Tis a time of War and Hazard, should it be now undertaken.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sol.</hi> 1. There are several things requisite to be prepared and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided; Several Manufactures relating to the Trade to be Erected, and Persons to be trained up and employed therein for some time, before it can be actually engaged in (after some Stock is provided) in which, the Stock, as it comes in gradually, will be improved to the Adventures Advantage, for their Encouragement to begin the same. And, It may be hoped, the War will have an end.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There are several Fishing Places so situated, as that they may be made use of very profitably, without considerable, if any Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, Loss or Damage: For that some Vessels will seldom need to lye or labour out of Sight and Protection of our own Shores: whereby we may be enabled to furnish our home Markets with Fish, at reasonable Rates.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If some Vessels should be Lost, the Stock being great, and managed by a Corporation for a Joynt accompt the damage would scarce be felt, and soon recovered, in so gainful a Trade.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A small Convoy or Guard on such Coasts will secure them; which the Letters Patents provides for.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> If it be said, We cannot build our Vessels, or Sail them, nor manage our Affairs to that advantage, that our Neighbours do.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sol.</hi> Many such Objections have been cast in, and probably will be revived to discourage the Undertaking, by amusing Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:207630:36"/> Persons. But the Error thereof is before evinced, by the Collections aforesaid, to the full Satisfaction of all that consider what is written; Touching either the providing Timber and other Materials for Building Fishing Vessels; Or the rates of Buildings within his Majesty's Kingdoms and Dominions; Or the providing of Salt, both better and cheaper; Or the saving the Duties impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, both on the Salt, and the Exportation of the Fish, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or the conveniencies of our situation for Exporting the same, to Countries that will take them off: And many other things obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable out of what is Collected as aforesaid. To which might have been added, an Abstract of Sr. <hi>Roger Le Strange</hi> his brief Treatise, to that purpose, entituled, <hi>A Discourse of the Fishery;</hi> briefly laying open not only the Advantages and Facility of the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, but likewise, the absolute necessity of it, in order to the well being both of King and People. Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1674. And,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quest.</hi> If any be desirous to know, or have an estimate of the ordinary charge of Building and Equipping a Fishing Vessel of about Seaventy Tun, for the First Year of its setting out, and so afterwards for Twenty Years, in Repairing and Amending the same, and all its Furniture. As also, What may be the Annual Profits thereof one Year with another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Answ.</hi> None may presume on what depends on God's Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Blessing, in the most prudent and diligent management of this Affair, more than of any other Maritine and Merchantly Adventures. But, Computing the Particulars of Profit and Loss, by others Observations and Experiences, it may be reasonably expected, That the disburse of about One thousand Pounds, in Building, Equipping, Victualling, and Wages of a Fishing Vessel of about Seaventy Tun, may produce <hi>Cent. per Cent. per Annum.</hi> For, So have very prying and experienced Men in the Fishing Trade computed; And such estimate thereof has been formerly presented to a Committee of Parliament, appointed to enquire about the Fishery Affair; And is evidenced by a small Treatise, called <hi>Britain's Buss,</hi> Printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1615. and Re-printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1630. setting forth the particulars.</p>
                  <p>But, Supposing it to be but half so much, or one quarter, <hi>(viz.</hi> 25 <hi>l. per Cent.</hi> clear Gains) 'twere sufficient encouragement and motive to incite all Persons to be concerned therein by their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptions: And the rather, for that 'tis so essentially requisite to the Strength, Safety, Wealth and Trade of these Kingdoms; and therefore is worthy the most serious Consideration and Regard
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:207630:37"/> of all true hearted <hi>English</hi> Men, of whatsoever Characters and Denominations amongst us; And ought accordingly to be so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged, as all the People of these Nations, who are able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute towards the Stock thereof may be admitted so to do; and thereby become engaged in Interest, to stand by and defend the Rights and Privileges of these Kingdoms, in the Fishings aforesaid; and not to be limited within the sole Power and Advantage of a few, the first Subscribers of the first Stock (proposed for the entring upon this Affair) exclusive of after Subscriptions, to as far as the Trade and Affairs thereof will bear and require.</p>
                  <p>In order whereunto, the Company of the Royal Fishery of <hi>England,</hi> Incorporated as aforesaid, in prosecution of this great Affair and Design, have caused, as well the Letters Patents for their Incorporation, as the Constitution, Laws, and Articles, Terms or Conditions of Subscription, and bringing in Persons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the said Company, to be Members of, or Traders, or Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers with them therein, to be fairly Ingrossed and Published in Books, to be exposed and opened for Subscriptions. As also, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracts of them to be Printed and Published, in order to Persons having the Contents thereof before them for their Consideration, before they do Subscribe.</p>
                  <p>The present Stock proposed by them is Three hundred thousand Pounds; Or One hundred and fifty thousand Pounds (at least) to begin the same withal: 'Tis made payable at Ten several Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Payments; and not any part thereof to be paid till Thirty days, from and after Notice or Publication of the compleating the said Subscriptions of the said first 150,000 <hi>l.</hi> As by their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Advertisements may appear.</p>
                  <p>Out of all which, 'tis evident, That there is (1.) a legal Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz.</hi> By Letters Patents or Charter from his late Majesty King <hi>Charles</hi> II. (2.) A regular Constitution and Laws, for the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Affairs of the Company, so as may be both safe and easy; unto which all the Members of the Company are to Subscribe, for the conservation, observing and keeping the same inviolably. And, (3.) Considerable Encouragements to the Subscribers of the said first 300,000 <hi>l.</hi> Not only by their Re-imbursment of their Tenth, by the Subscribers of the next 300,000 <hi>l.</hi> as aforesaid, which is proposed to be allowed for the first Patentees, and such Disburs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Losses, Charges and Damages, as the Members of the Company have sustained, in the management and preserving the Patent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in being, to this time; and other uses of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:207630:37"/> entrusted by the Constitution, to be distributed by the Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stees of the Company; but by Three <hi>per Cent.</hi> allowed to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribers of the first One hundred and fifty thousand Pounds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, out of their Three first Quarterly Payments, by equal propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: All which, notwithstanding, is also to be made good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Stock of the Company, by and out of the said tenth part, proposed as aforesaid.</p>
                  <p>And, to the end that Persons in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the remote Parts of <hi>England,</hi> might not be surprized or excluded the first Subscriptions and benefits thereof, (if they should think sit to begin so early) The Company, by their Order of the third day of <hi>June</hi> last, deferred their taking Subscriptions unto the third day of <hi>September</hi> following; and resolved, That should have been the day of opening their Books, for the said whole Sum of 300,000 <hi>l.</hi> And that they would speedily agree and notify the place or places for doing thereof: Which having been notified, Several worthy Persons of the City of <hi>London</hi> and Parts adjacent, became enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in Subscriptions and Promises, to the the value of about 50,000 <hi>l.</hi> (in case the Books should be then opened for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose). Whereupon the Company thought meet to have their Books opened accordingly for such value. But,</p>
                  <p>Upon further Considerations, (as namely, That most Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament, and others of the Nobility and Gentry, were out of Town, and were not likely to come sooner than about the beginning of the next Term: And, that it was meet for the Company to provide they should not be precluded of any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, proposed to the Subscribers of the first 300,000 <hi>l.)</hi> The Company therefore, by their further Order of the 31st day of <hi>August</hi> last, thought fit, upon the Subscriptions of the said 50,000 <hi>l.</hi> to restrain any further Subscriptions, or Opening of their Books for that purpose, until the Fourth day of <hi>November</hi> next: And having (in Nine days time) received Subscriptions of the said 50,000 <hi>l.</hi> they shut up their Books accordingly: And have ordered the same should be Published; and that they will no longer, than the said Fourth day of <hi>November</hi> next, delay the Subscriptions, that any Persons shall think fit further to make, for raising the said Stock, and settling their other Affairs, relating to the management thereof. And, in the mean time, will live in hopes of the Parliaments Confirmation of, and Additions to their Privileges, herein before mentioned, to have been formerly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:207630:38"/> granted to the Undertakers; Whereunto they are encouraged, by the Judgment of the Parliament of this Kingdom, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Preamble of an Act, past in the Fourteenth year of his late Majesty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, <hi>Cap.</hi> 28. wherein is this Expression, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Publick Honour, Wealth and Safety of this Realm, as well in the maintenance of Trade, and support of Navigation, as in many other Respects, doth in an high degree depend upon the Improvement of the <hi>Fishery, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Which may be thus Paraphrased, <hi>viz.</hi> The Fish of the British Seas, and other his Majesty's Dominions, within the Grant afore-specified, (which costs us nothing but the taking) being added to our other useful and necessary Products and Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, wherewith these Kingdoms and Dominions are Blessed, (beyond any other trading Nations of the World; wherein also consists the Honour of these Islands) may be Exported to double, yea treble the value of all necessary Imports of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes from other Countries, And so must necessarily produce great Wealth of all kinds, and particularly plenty of Monies, for its Ballance. And, The Fishings train up multitudes of the hardiest and skilfullest Seamen for our other Navigations and Defence: In the improvement whereof Principally, lies the Safety and Strength of these Nations: And the situation of these Islands being such, as may justly challenge to be the Emporium or Mart of Trade beyond all others, We shall not need to fear the vent of such Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plussage of such Imports, for ready Monies of all Countries who need them. And, if so, (not regarding the Malicious and Clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destine Whisperings and Backbitings of such as envy and bear ill will to our Nations Flourishing, under our present Government, and the ways and means proposed for the management of this Affair (which they understand little of) let all the Cordial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters thereof be up and doing: And if our only Strength fail us not, we may bid Defiance in his Name to all the Might of Europe; which shall conclude this Subject: With this brief Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertisement of the Collector hereof, Touching the present State
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:207630:38"/> of these Kingdoms, with respect to the present advance of our Gold and other Monies, above the common Standard and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination at which they are Coyned; <hi>viz.</hi> That the same is Impoverishing and Destructive to the Trade, Prosperity and Wealth of these Nations. That yet the Government may be eased of the burthen of our Clipped Monies, without charge or loss to the Nation; yea, to the great enriching thereof, and so as may tend to the carrying on the Fishery; The present War with the <hi>French,</hi> And all its Tradings whatsoever, To the excess of Profit and Commodity before mentioned; The methods and means of which he reserves to the further Prosecution of what he hath heretofore humbly proposed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>